<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An addition or postscript to The vindication of the essence and unity of the Church-Catholick visible, and the priority thereof in regard of particular churches. In answer to the objections made against it, both by Mr. Stone, and some others. / By Samuel Hudson ...</title>
            <author>Hudson, Samuel, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86680</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202480</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">49241710</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 49241710</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170879</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86680)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170879)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2501:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An addition or postscript to The vindication of the essence and unity of the Church-Catholick visible, and the priority thereof in regard of particular churches. In answer to the objections made against it, both by Mr. Stone, and some others. / By Samuel Hudson ...</title>
                  <author>Hudson, Samuel, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.B. for Andrew Kembe ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ellis, John, 1606?-1681. --  Vindiciae Catholicae.</term>
               <term>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647. --  A survey of the summe of church discipline.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170879:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170879:1"/>
            <p>AN Addition or Poſtſcript TO THE VINDICATION OF THE ESSENCE and UNITY OE THE Church-Catholick viſible, And the Priority thereof in regard of Particular CHURCHES.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to the Objections made againſt it, both by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Stone,</hi> and ſome others.</p>
            <p>By SAMUEL HUDSON, Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Capell</hi> in <hi>Suff.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Eccleſiam teneo tritico &amp; paleâ plenam, emendo quos poſſum, tolero quos emendare non poſſum: fugio paleam, ne hoc ſim, non aream, ne nihil ſim.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug. Ep. 48. contra Don.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. B.</hi> for <hi>Andrew Kembe,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop neer S. <hi>Margarets</hi> hill in <hi>Southwark,</hi> and by <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Brewſter</hi> at the <hi>Crane</hi> in <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard, and <hi>Thomas Baſſet</hi> under <hi>Dunſtanes</hi> Church <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> 1658.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170879:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:170879:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170879:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170879:3"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſecond impreſſion of the Vindication of the Eſſence and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church-Catholick, viſible, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> came to the birth altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my knowledge of the Stationer, or his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and without his knowledge of me, and mine intention: and it was ſo far paſſed in the Preſs before I knew of it, that there was no recalling of it. I had another Copy of it almoſt ready for the Preſs, wherein I had given anſwer to M. <hi>Stone,</hi> and ſome other opponents in their proper places in the Book.</p>
            <p>Alſo I had obliterated the name of my antient friend M. <hi>Ellis,</hi> who had written in oppoſition to my firſt Theſis upon this queſtion, and had left out all perſonall reflections upon him, to which I was in a manner, neceſſitated in my former impreſſion to vindicate my ſelf; and therefore I muſt crave his indulgence for this impreſſion, the coming out where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> (ſo as it is) being wholly againſt my minde. The Book ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving met with ſome oppoſition, and that in Print, from ſome reverend brethren, I thought not fit to let this impreſſion of it paſs into the world, without taking notice of what was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected against it, and therefore am conſtrained to play
<pb facs="tcp:170879:4"/>
an after-game, and to add theſe few ſheets as a Postſcript thereunto.</p>
            <p>I have not as yet, met with any thing in print, which ſhould cauſe me to alter my judgment about the main ſubject of the Book, and yet I dare not ſay but ſome paſſages in it, may be carped at, and are liable to exceptions againſt; for I am but a frail man, and ſee but in part, and ſo am ſubject to erre, as well as others; yet am willing to be reclaimed in whatſoever I miſtake at any time, and would not willingly bee miſ-led, much leſs miſ-lead others.</p>
            <p>The ſubject is ſomething knotty and difficult, and not apt to be underſtood by every Reader, and therefore let him that readeth conſider it well, that ſo he may underſtand, and not paſs a cenſure raſhly upon it before he underſtands it. That the Lord would guide thee and me into all truth, is the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſts worthleſs ſervant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SAMUEL HUDSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="vindication">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170879:4"/>
            <head>THE VINDICATION OF THE Eſſence and Unity OF THE Church-Catholick viſible, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince the firſt publiſhing of the ſame, which was 1649. hath met with various enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment amongſt men, according to the various judgments of the readers thereof; as Books of polemical ſubjects, ſuch as this is, uſe to do. From ſome it obtained acceptation and approbation, from others it met with improbation, and oppoſition. Two things eſpecially have been oppoſed therein. Firſt, the being of an univerſal viſible Church, which is the ſubject of the ſecond and third Chapters of this Vindication, and the former Chapter proving it by Scripture, the latter by arguments and reaſons. Secondly, the integrality of the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal viſible Church, handled in the fourth Chapter is oppoſed.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170879:5"/>
The eſſence or being of it, is oppoſed lately in print, by ſome Miniſters in <hi>Norfolk</hi> and <hi>Suffolk,</hi> in their anſwer to <hi>Jus Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Miniſterii Evangelici,</hi> ſet forth by the Provinciall Aſſembly in <hi>London,</hi> and to <hi>Vindiciae Miniſterii Evangelici,</hi> ſet forth by M. <hi>John Collings</hi> of <hi>Norwich.</hi> But becauſe this was not the main ſcope of their book, only they lighted upon it in their Epiſtle Dedicatory; I ſhall leave them to their proper opponents, and only anſwer to what they ſay in their Epiſtle concerning this ſubject. The integrality of the univerſall viſible Church hath been oppoſed by M. <hi>Stone,</hi> a reverend Miniſter and teacher to the Church of Chriſt at <hi>Hartford</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> and my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient acquaintance. And this was in a tractate, called, A <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational Church is a Catholick Church;</hi> which came forth in print, 1652. To whom I never intended to return an anſwer in any particular Treatiſe, partly becauſe I ſaw his book was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a logical Lecture, and of ſo abſtruſe and ſublime a ſubject, that as it was little taken notice of, ſo it was leſs underſtood by any, but thoſe ſchollars that were verſed in thoſe ſtudies, and ſo muſt mine anſwer have been alſo. And partly becauſe he only or cheifly oppoſed the arguments which I ſet down in my fourth Chapter, and dealt not with the whole book, or the main ſcope of my Vindication, or queſtion: and therein alſo oppoſed only thoſe arguments which I brought againſt M. <hi>Ellis,</hi> which were taken from principles and grounds which I knew M. <hi>Ellis</hi> grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which was warrant ſufficient for to me uſe them, though M. <hi>Stone</hi> granted them not. And in them alſo M. <hi>Stone</hi> miſtook my meaning, for by my denying the univerſal Church to be a <hi>genus,</hi> I did not deny it to an exiſting <hi>genus,</hi> or <hi>genus in actu exercito,</hi> which M. <hi>Stone</hi> argued for; for I knew though it were an integral, it muſt be of one kinde or other, but I denyed that it could put on the notion or conſideration of a Church <hi>in genere.</hi> So, that my queſtion about the integrality of the univerſal Church was no whit impaired by his arguments, though they had all been granted, only thoſe arguments taken neceſſarily from principles granted by M. <hi>Ellis</hi> might have been invalidated thereby. And partly becauſ I ſaw that M. <hi>Stone</hi> did implicitely grant what I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for, which was, that the univerſal Church is not the <hi>genus</hi> of particular Congregations, in that he aſſigneth another <hi>genus</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170879:5"/>
to them in the frontiſpice of his book, and upon the top of every page in his book, and that is Congregation <hi>in genere.</hi> But I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that if ever this vindication ſhould again com to the Preſs, I would have explained my meaning more fully, and that I meant by <hi>genus</hi> Church <hi>in genere,</hi> and not the integral nature of the <hi>genus</hi> that exiſteth in individuals, and ſo to have inſerted an anſwer to M. <hi>Stone</hi> in that my fourth Chapter, which now I am prevented in, by this ſurreptitious coming forth of this ſecond Edition without my knowledge, and therefore I have added this Poſtſcript. I firſt therefore ſhall clear that there is a Church-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick viſible.</p>
            <p>Some of our brethren which have lately written, tell us that a particular Church is a particular company of Saints in mutuall union, for mutuall worſhip appointed by Chriſt for the glory of God, and the edification of their own ſouls, and the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. I intend not to carp, but ſhall give as candid an interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation as may be of their words. I ſuppoſe by <hi>Saints</hi> they mean viſible Saints, Saints by dedication and conſecration, and not abſolutely of Saints by regeneration, for as they have no certain rules to judge thereof in others, ſo alſo they can never be ſure they are in a true Church, but will ſtill be ſcrupulous in their communion, and cannot diſpenſe or communicate in faith, but doubtingly. They are alſo very tender in expreſſing the form, or as ſome will have it, the <hi>Cement</hi> of this particular ſociety, and therefore have left out the word Covenant, either explicite or implicite: and ſo I hope they intend to let in parochial Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations into the definition, though not independent, for there is ſuch a <hi>mutual union</hi> among them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For mutual worſhip,</hi> I ſuppoſe they mean joining in publick worſhip, and not as we ſpeak of mutuall duties between man and wife, to be performed to each others, but worſhip performed by them jointly to God, But I marvell that this definition menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons not any relation of this particular Church to ſome officer or officers to whom they ſhould ſubject themſelves, and by whom they ſhould be taught, edified, and governed, and who ſhould be Gods mouth to them, and their mouth to God. I am loth to be too bold or peremtory in gueſſing at their meaning: but hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is becauſe they intend to put the keys of diſcipline into the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170879:6"/>
body of this Congregation, which can exerciſe them without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, or becauſe they can ſet up un-ordained private members to preach and pray among them, and ſo make up their mutual wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip alſo without an officer or Ambaſſadour of Chriſt, <hi>to whom is committed the word of reconciliation;</hi> for indeed that is the ſcope of their book, though they do acknowledge that there ought to be ſuch officers: or haply they feared to be unchurched again by the death of ſuch an officer, if they had put him into their definition. They ſay alſo that the end of this mutual union is for the edification of their own ſouls, but that muſt imply them all truly converted; but I mervail that they make no proviſion in their definition, for the education, inſtruction, and converſion of children born members of their Congregation, and ſervants of their members, ſeeing by Gods appointment, and the uſage in Old and New Teſtament, the parent or maſter brings his whole family into covenant aswel as himſelf and a part of the Miniſters office is <hi>to go to the loſt ſheep of the houſe Iſrael,</hi> to convert uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted perſons, as well as edifie converted. They ſay nothing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of their mutual inſpection and watching over one another, for which this way is ſo highly cryed up above others: haply it is becauſe their members dwel ſo far remote, in ſo many pariſhes, that they ſee it is impoſſible to do it.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"They grant an univerſal company of Saints, in a reformed ſenſe, comprehending every individual Saint-member thereof, whether formed into fellowſhip or unformed: but as Saints, not as Churches of Saints.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I acknowledge it is true the particular viſible believers are the matter of the univerſal Church, whether formed into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations or no, for that is but a ſecondary accidental relation that betideth them, and enters not into the eſſence of their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</p>
            <p>It is true, their particular memberſhip of this or that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation coms by their union with it; but were they not mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and ſubjects of Chriſts political viſible Kingdom before any ſuch union, and initiated into it by one of his officers, yet not as a particular officer of a Congregation, for none are baptized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Congregation but as by an indefinite officer of the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal viſible Church of Chriſt: And an indefinite officer in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170879:6"/>
to his imployment, and general object, is equivalent to a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and that is the prime relation of a Miniſter, and that to a particular Congregation is ſecondary, as it conſiſts of a parcel of the univerſal Church, over whom he takes eſpecial, actual, conſtant, care and charge.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"They ſay the <hi>World</hi> is univerſal, of which all creatures are a part, yet did a man ſtand where he might ſee all Countries, and all crearures, he ſhould ſee but a particular world; really par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, but intellectually univerſal.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> If by particular world, they mean in relation to a general world, it is not true; for one particular cannot make up an univerſal; and there was never any world but this one. But if by particular they mean an individual integral world, it is true, and that is it which I contend for in this Vindication; that the univerſal or Oecumenical Church cannot put on the notion of a Church <hi>in genere,</hi> but of a great individual integral: and ſo both the world, and univerſal Church are, whether a man ſtands where he can ſee them or no: they are <hi>integraliter univerſale</hi> as <hi>Ames</hi> calls the univerſal Church.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"It is true that they ſay, did a man ſtand where he might ſee all the Corporations, and all particular civil ſocieties of men, he might acknowledge the general nature of Corporations exiſting in either of them <hi>(or the integral nature rather, and from them all abſtract a general nature)</hi> and yet deny an univerſal Corporation, conſiſting of them as parts thereof.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But this comes to paſs becauſe the ſeveral Corporations or polities are conſtituted by ſeveral Charters, granted from ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſovereigns, under ſeveral laws.</p>
            <p>But the univerſal Church hath but one Charter, from one ſovereign, under the ſame ſyſteme of laws, and the officers inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, officers in reference to their imploiment to which they are called by Chriſt, and may exerciſe the ſame towards any of the ſubjects of that whole Eccleſiaſtical body, as they have opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and a call: which the officers of the ſeveral civil Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions cannot do.</p>
            <p>They anſwer that text, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>God hath ſet in the Church firſt Apoſtles, ſecondarily Prophets, &amp;c.</hi> which is uſually brought to prove an univerſal viſible Church, by paralleling it with what
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170879:7"/>
is ſaid <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>God hath ſet the members every one in the body.</hi> And if that will not conclude a Catholick body, neither will the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer conclude a Catholick Church.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, the difference between them is great: for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral bodies, though they may have a general conſideration and notion put upon them, or abſtracted from them rather, of body <hi>in genere,</hi> yet are they not united together into one individual bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by any external bond, they are not <hi>integrally</hi> one, but only <hi>generically</hi> or <hi>ſpecifically</hi> one. But the univerſal Church is united in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one body by a viſible external bond, yea bonds of the ſame Sovereign, the ſame Laws, the ſame Covenant, the ſame Initiation and enrowlment, and the ſame indefinite Officers over it. And this is the primary conſideration that coms upon it, before any particular diſtinctions into Congregations, which conſiſt of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells of that great body. And therefore that which the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>ver.</hi> 27. <hi>ye are the body of Chriſt, and members in particular,</hi> is meant, ye are of the body of Chriſt, or part of the body of Chriſt, not the whole, for Chriſt hath but one body, in the ſame reſpect, and ye are particular members thereof.</p>
            <p>They bring diverſe arguments againſt an univerſall viſible Church.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 1.</note>Their firſt argument is, becauſe every part is incompleat, not having the power of a whole in it; but every particular Church rightly conſtituted hath in it the power of a whole Church; therefore it is not a part.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is true, every part hath not the <hi>extenſive</hi> power of the whole, it hath the compleatneſs of a part, and no more. Every civil Corporation is called a body politick, and it is compleat according to the conſtitution of it, but this hinders it not from being a member of a greater body politick, <hi>viz.</hi> the Kingdom or Common-wealth whereto it belongeth. So every particular Congregation hath the compleatneſs of a particular Church in it, but ſtill as it is a part of the whole Church, which is the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt on earth. It is an integral or whole in reference to its particular members, but in reference to the reſt of the Church it is but a member.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 2.</note>Again they ſay, that every whole is really diſtinct from every part, and from all the parts collectively conſidered. They are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting, that is conſtituted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170879:7"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So I may ſay of all the viſible believers in the world, they may in conſideration be diſtinguiſhed from the whole, and all the members of the body from the whole, becauſ they conſtitute it: but they being all the conſtituent members joined in an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty make up the whole conſtituted Church or body: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that argument was no better then a fallacy. For I can ſay the ſame of all the members of a Congregation both publick and private, they are diſtinct from the whole, for they are conſtituent, and that is conſtituted: but as they are united they are one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Congregation; ſo are all the viſible private Chriſtians and Miniſters united, one univerſal viſible Church: In conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration indeed they may be diſtinct, yet by political conjunction in the political Kingdom of Chriſt they are one whole.</p>
            <p>Again they ſay, there is no univerſal meeting to worſhip God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 3.</note> therefore there is no univerſal Church.</p>
            <p>So neither is there ever a meeting of all the ſubjects of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or Common-wealth to do homage or ſervice to their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign, but they all obey him <hi>diviſim</hi> in their places,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> or ſome ſmaller conventions, and yet they are a whole Kingdom or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth nevertheleſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is never uſed either in a civil, or ſacred ſenſe, but <hi>propter conventum:</hi> and <hi>coetus eſt à co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ëundo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> properly ſignifieth a calling out, and not a calling together: And in a ſacred ſenſe it ſignifieth a people cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led either out of the world, as the inviſible Church is, or from Idols as the viſible Church is. The members thereof are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, perſons called out; and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are <hi>conjugata,</hi> and they relate to, and argue one another. The particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation is rather <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the ſtricteſt ſenſe in reference to their meeting together, then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>So <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whence the Scotiſh word Kirk, and our Engliſh word Church comes, properly ſignifieth the Lord's people. And this notion betideth people not primarily becauſe they are of this or that Congregation, but becauſe they are of the Kingdom of Chriſt, and have given their hand to the Lord. And the word <hi>coetus</hi> and <hi>congregatio</hi> more properly reſpects them that as they meet together in an Aſſembly. Heathens may <hi>coïre</hi> come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170879:8"/>
even into a ſacred Aſſembly, but becauſe they are not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> called from their Idols to Chriſt, they are not part of the Church, though they be parts of the Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 4.</note>Again, they ſay, there are no diſtinct office<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s appointed for ſuch a diſtinct Church, therefore there is no ſuch Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though there are no diſtinct officers of the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church beſides the officers of particular Churches, or ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Miniſters of the Word, yet every Miniſter hath an indefinite office, which ſtands in relation to his imployment, which he may put forth any where in the whole Church, as occaſion ſerveth, and he hath a call thereto, which is equivalent to a generall office.</p>
            <p>Every Miniſter of the Word hath power <hi>in actu primo</hi> to diſpenſe the Word and Sacraments, to pray and bleſs the people in any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred convention, though the members of that Aſſembly be not members of any one particular Congregation, and though the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter himſelf be not fixed to, or ſet actually over any particular Congregation. And that meeting ſhal be a ſacred convention, not only in reſpect of the Ordinances or Miniſter, but in reſpect of the members of it, becauſe they are all the Lord's people <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the proper &amp; primary ſenſe, and he the Lord's Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor deſigned to that imployment. The body of the whole Church being ſo great, and conſiſting of perſons of ſeveral Countries, and languages, and under ſeveral civil governours, haply at variance between themſelves, it was not convenient, nor ſcarce poſſible to have any conſtant ordinary actual officers of the whole, but that is ſalved by their habitual power of office, which may be drawn forth any where into act as occaſion ſerveth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 5.</note>Again, they ſay, there is no Church greater then that which hath the power to hear and determine upon offences committed in the Church, but that is particular, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. which place ſay they, if it meaneth the Congregation, it excludeth all other, if it meaneth any other it excludes the Congregation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhall let M. <hi>Parker</hi> anſwer this argument, who ſaith in <hi>Pol. Eccl. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 355. though he held particular Congregations the prime Churches in reference to Synods, yet grounds the more general or greater Aſſemblies for diſcipline upon this text, <hi>per gradationem, &amp; per ſequeiam ratiocinandi &amp; per conſequentiam,</hi> as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170879:8"/>
I noted in my <hi>vind.</hi> 163. And this appears by the gradation in the text from one to two or three, and from two or three to the Church, and if the Church cannot end it, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they cannot, then by the like manner of reaſoning it is to be referred to a greater number of Elders convened.</p>
            <p>For doubtleſs Chriſt did not mean by Church the body of the Church, but the Elders, for the body of the people never had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny right of judicature among the Jews, nor in the Chriſtian Churches, though I ſuppoſe ſome of our brethren would infer ſo from this text. And it is very probable that our Lord Chriſt ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the people of the Jews, ſpake to them in their own dialect, of Courts then ſet up, where there were appeals from the three Judges to 23, and from the 23 to the Sanedrin or ſeventy one El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. For Chriſt had not then inſtituted any Chriſtian Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations or juriſdictions; and if Chriſt had ſpoken of what was not in being as the people he ſpake to could have no relief there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, ſo they could not underſtand him. Now if primarily he meant the three Judges or Rulers of the Synagogue, yet that did not exclude the 23, and if he meant primarily the 23, that did not exclude the Sanedrin; ſo in Chriſtian juriſdictions, which for the general nature were to be like the Jewiſh, though not in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular circumſtance, the bringing a cauſe to a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall Elderſhip excludes not the Claſſis, nor the Claſſis a Provincial Synod. Though the Jewiſh politie was not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be pulled down, and the Chriſtian to ſucceed, yet it was not then pulled down, but ſtood <hi>jure divino,</hi> though many of the perſons in thoſe offices were corrupt, and the people as yet were bound by Gods law to make uſe of them, and be determined by them. Our Lord Chriſt ſends the cleanſed Lepers to the Prieſts to offer for them, though they were generally wicked. And in his ſermon, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.22. he clearly alludes to their preſent judicatures.</p>
            <p>Afterward the ſame Authours except againſt the definition of the office of the Miniſtry ſet down by the Province of <hi>London,</hi> in their <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> &amp;c. Becauſe they make it a relation to the whole imployment of the Miniſtry. But whether you call it right or power, or authority given them by commiſſion, or what gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral nature or notion can be put upon it, it is certain it was in relation to the whole imployment of the Miniſtry, as they well
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170879:9"/>
clear it up. That was the ſubject wherein they had power by their office or ſunction to deal, and be exerciſed in. <hi>To them was committed the word of reconciliation.</hi> And therefore the Miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all office is ſet out in Scripture thereby, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.4. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.2. as I noted more at large in <hi>vind.</hi> 233. And though there muſt needs be an object, <hi>viz.</hi> perſons to whom they are to adminiſter the Word, yet that object in their commiſſion is not ſet down in Scripture to be particular Congregations on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but <hi>go teach all Nations and baptize them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and lo, I am with you always to the end of the World,</hi> Mat 28.19, 20. <hi>And go ye into all the world, and preach the Goſpel to every creature,</hi> Mar. 16.15. And ſo likewiſe adminiſter the other Otdinances to them when you have made them capable of them.</p>
            <p>And the Argument which thoſe Brethren inſiſt upon from <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeta</hi> is of no force; for though as they are particular Miniſters of ſuch a flock, indeed that particular relation ceaſeth, if the flock ceaſeth &amp;c. but the generall relation to the whole remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſo that there is a correlate object ſtill as long as there are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny believers that ſtand in need of edifying by their office, or any meer viſible believers, or their children or ſervants that ſtand in need of inſtruction, exhortation, reproofe, or internall conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, &amp;c. And if all thoſe ſhould ceaſe, yet they ſhall find objects for their Miniſtry, as long as there be any reaſonable creatures under heaven; as M. <hi>Norton</hi> in his anſwer to <hi>Apollon. pag.</hi> 81. wel obſerveth, where he ſaith, that when they preach to heathens it is a miniſterial act in regard of the diſpenſer and adminiſtrer. <hi>Habent Miniſtri poteſtatem Miniſterialem non Eccleſiaſticam er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga univerſum mundum, &amp; erga omnem creaturam.</hi> And therefore he pleadeth that the Miniſters have Miniſterial power <hi>in modo debito erga omnem Eccleſiam,</hi> Or elſe ſaith he, the heathens ſhould be in better caſe then the neighbour Churches, if it were Miniſterial preaching to them, and not to neighbour Churches. He ſaith, no duty of Miniſterial acts of office in other Churches is to be denied, <hi>p.</hi> 82. ſo it be regulated.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> were called forth by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 13. and ſent out with faſting and praier, and impoſition of hands to go to the heathen; was it a Miniſterial work which they performed, or a Chari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ative? If a Miniſterial work of their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170879:9"/>
office, then not onely the particular Congregation, or the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church, but the very heathens are the object of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial office, as it is an office.</p>
            <p>The Scripture ſpeaking ſo indefinitely of the office of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, under the name of Miniſtry, makes it appear that their office related to the imployment or ſubject thereof, &amp; not only to a few perſons in Congregational Covenant, or particular mutual u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them. See <hi>Act.</hi> 20.24. and 21.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.7. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. And hath not the Miniſter the ſame ſubject and object that the Miniſtry hath, ſeeing the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry is committed to him.</p>
            <p>If a Miniſter of the Church in <hi>England</hi> ſhould baptize a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Jew, Turk, or heathen, he doth not do it as a Miniſter of a particular Congregation, or of the Church in <hi>England,</hi> but as an indefinite Officer of Chriſt, to whom he hath committed that employment: and ſo the office reacheth that forreigner, not as a member of the Church in <hi>England,</hi> for ſo he never was, and haply never will be, but as a new ſubject added to Chriſt's viſible Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhal ſhew that the univerſal Church is an integral, and not Church <hi>in genere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I enter upon this Chapter, which hath been oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in print by M. <hi>Stone</hi> a reverend Miniſter in <hi>New-England;</hi> it will be requiſite for me to premiſe ſomthing in general, and then anſwer his particular Objections againſt the ſeveral arguments as they lie in order.</p>
            <p>It was mine unhappineſs to fall into the hands of two reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Divines, whoſe principles of Logick, and eſpecially concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Genus,</hi> were different from each other; and ſo while I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the univerſal Church to be no <hi>genus</hi> according to the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and expreſs grants of the former in his <hi>Vindiciae Catholicae</hi> which I cited, who was an <hi>Ariſtotelian;</hi> the other underſtanding <hi>genus</hi> in another ſenſe, being a <hi>Ramiſt,</hi> oppoſeth my arguments, denying the <hi>Ariſtotelian</hi> principles, which the former went up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and granted, whereas it was ſufficient for one to prove the univerſal Church not to be a <hi>genus</hi> by his own principles whom I anſwered.</p>
            <p>So it fareth with me, as I have ſeen it with a Country man
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170879:10"/>
in a crowd, who being ſtricken a box on one ear, and turning himſelf to ſee who ſtruck him, and to defend himſelf on that hand, was ſtricken by another on the other ear, and ſo was fain to turn again to defend himſelf on that ſide alſo. M. <hi>Ellis</hi> took <hi>genus</hi> to be a logical or metaphyſical abſtract non-exiſting notion, as he acknowledges in print, and upon his own grant: I dealt with him; M. <hi>Stone</hi> taketh <hi>genus</hi> to be an exiſting being, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, and ſhewing his face in every individual, whether wee ſee it or no, and thereupon diſputes againſt my arguments, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then M. <hi>Ellis</hi> could have done, and ſo puts me upon a new Vindication, by denying the principles upon which my argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were built, which principles the former granted freely. If I had thought the word <hi>genus</hi> would have met with ſuch oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, I ſhould have ſet down my meaning more warily, and for <hi>genus</hi> have ſet general, or <hi>in genere,</hi> or in general conſideration, which was my meaning, and ſo he whom I anſwered underſtood it, and M. <hi>Stone</hi> might have ſeen that was my meaning alſo. The paucity of words, and multitude of things is the cauſe why the ſame word is uſed for many things, and ſo is taken in a different ſenſe, and ſo it falls out in the word <hi>genus,</hi> for ſomtimes it ſignifieth a Stock, Linage, Parentage, Kindred, or Family as M. <hi>Stone</hi> in his Tractate, <hi>p.</hi> 2. from <hi>Act.</hi> 4.6. and <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.5. notes. And ſomtime it is taken for that common nature which exiſteth in the individuals, as humane nature in <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>animal</hi> in man and brute, &amp;c. And ſomtime it ſignifyeth an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract notion ariſing from this community of nature, or a thing <hi>in genere,</hi> or general conſideration, and in that ſenſe M. <hi>Ellis</hi> took it, and ſo I formed my arguments in his own ſenſe. But concerning the exiſting <hi>genus</hi> which M. <hi>Stone</hi> ſpeaks of, I cannot ſee how it can agree with the definition which himſelf giveth of it out of <hi>Ramus;</hi> which is, <hi>Genus eſt totum partibus,</hi> i. e. <hi>ſpeciebus eſſentiale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For that which doth exiſt, exiſteth in ſome individual, and there is neither a <hi>totum</hi> or whole, nor eſſential to the <hi>ſpecies.</hi> It is not a <hi>totum,</hi> for <hi>Totum eſt quod habet partes:</hi> indeed it may have its parts, that is members, as it is an integral, but the parts of a <hi>genus</hi> are his <hi>ſpecies.</hi> The exiſting <hi>animal</hi> that is in <hi>Peter</hi> is not a <hi>generical</hi> whole, for it is but a part of <hi>Peter,</hi> and hath no <hi>ſpecies</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170879:10"/>
under it. The truth is, it is an eſſential part of <hi>Peter,</hi> for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>totum continet ſuas partes,</hi> that <hi>animal</hi> in <hi>Peter</hi> is wholly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in <hi>Peter,</hi> and holden there by <hi>Peters</hi> form; and as ſoon as <hi>Peters</hi> form left him, that <hi>animal</hi> was gone. Again, <hi>totum eſt majus qualibet parte,</hi> but Peter is <hi>major hoc animale,</hi> he contains the animal and more than it. Hence <hi>Downam</hi> upon <hi>Ramus</hi> ſaith, <hi>hinc apparet genus ſpeciei &amp; totum &amp; partem eſſe, totum quidem prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatione, &amp; communi ſignificatione, quâ ſpecies continet: pars ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò ſi ad conſtitutionem reſpiciamus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the giving eſſence, or being eſſential to a thing reſpecteth the conſtitution in every exiſting thing. <hi>Boëthus</hi> alſo ſaith, <hi>Genus in diviſione totum eſt in definitione pars. Species contra, in diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one pars eſt, in definitione totum.</hi> Neither is that <hi>genus</hi> that exiſteth in an individual <hi>partibus</hi> i. e. <hi>ſpeciebus eſſentiale,</hi> for it giveth its eſſence to that individual, and hath no influence upon any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when thoſe men and brutes that are now alive die, then die thoſe phyſical exiſting <hi>genus's</hi> indeed, but the logical abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>genus</hi> of them dyeth not: the phyſical individual <hi>genus's</hi> are renewed by generation, but the logical <hi>genus</hi> of them is not ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated but abſtracted, and is the ſame from the beginning of the world to the end: it ever was, and ever will be a true axiome, <hi>homo eſt animal rationale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here M. <hi>Stone</hi> helpeth himſelf with a diſtinction of <hi>genus in actu ſignato &amp; actu exercito, p.</hi> 7. I know not well what he mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thereby, or how he will apply it to the cauſe in hand. But <hi>Scheibler in his Metaph. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>art.</hi> 5. ſaith, <hi>Apprehenditur res in actu ſignato, cum concipitur ſic, prout communi definitione ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; ſub proprio ſigno</hi> i. e. <hi>nomine apprehenditur. In actu exercito apprehenditur cum concipitur aliquid non communi, ſed particulari, dimiſſo communi nomine.</hi> So that it layeth aſide his common name and notion of a <hi>genus in actu exercito,</hi> and is but an integral un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it. <hi>Jacob. Martin. in diſput.</hi> 2 <hi>metaph, theſ.</hi> 60. ſaith <hi>Actus ſignatus vocatur a ſingularibus abſtractus. Actus exercitus eſt actus in ſingularibus multiplicatus</hi> i. e. in individuals and integrals un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that kinde. And further <hi>Scheibler</hi> giveth this inſtance to clear it. <hi>Genus praedicatur de ſpecie. Hoc verum eſt, loquendo de eo in actu exercito, non in actu ſignato, hoc eſt genus praedicatur de ſpecie non ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendo communes notiones, ſive nomina generis &amp; ſpeciei, ſed particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laria
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170879:11"/>
exempla,</hi> which particular examples are the integrals under that kinde.</p>
            <p>But this diſtinction will not help him; for if <hi>genus in actu ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercito</hi> be not a <hi>totum</hi> or whole, but a part, and be not <hi>eſſentiale ſpeciebus</hi> but only <hi>uni individuo,</hi> then it is not <hi>genus.</hi> If the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and notion of <hi>genus</hi> cannot agree to it, it is not <hi>genus.</hi> The definition of <hi>integrum</hi> agreeth to every example of an <hi>integrum,</hi> it is a whole made up of his members, but the definition of <hi>genus</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to none of thoſe which he calls examples of <hi>genus.</hi> In that it wanteth or loſeth its univerſality, it wants and loſeth its <hi>genus</hi> and its difference or form: for the very eſſence of <hi>genus</hi> (by his logick) is to be a whole, and to give eſſence to its <hi>ſpecies.</hi> It hath but a piece of the <hi>genus,</hi> and a piece of the form: it hath <hi>integram naturam generis, non univerſam,</hi> as M. <hi>Stone</hi> ſaith <hi>p.</hi> 4. and <hi>Richardſon</hi> out of whom he had it ſaith the ſame. Then if it hath only the integral nature, and not the univerſal, it hath it not as it is a <hi>genus,</hi> but as it is an integral, for the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>genus</hi> lyeth in the univerſality, which the individual hath not. Though there be an <hi>Ens,</hi> ſubſtance, body, and animal in <hi>Peter,</hi> yet they are as individual as <hi>Peter:</hi> and the <hi>Ens,</hi> ſubſtance, body, and animal in <hi>Peter,</hi> differ every way as much as the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity in <hi>Peter</hi> differs from that which is in <hi>Paul,</hi> or as <hi>Petriety</hi> differs from <hi>Pauliety,</hi> or <hi>Socratiety</hi> from <hi>Platoniety,</hi> to uſe his own expreſſions. <hi>Socrates</hi> conſiſteth of <hi>hoc Ens, haec ſubſtantia, hoc cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, hoc animal,</hi> and <hi>hic homo;</hi> and ſo all theſe kindes are under contraction and individuation. <hi>Quicquid eſt in Socrate ſingulare eſt. Fonſec. Metaph.</hi> Take all the individuals of one ſort that ever were, are, or ſhall be in the world, and you cannot make one <hi>totum univerſale</hi> of them, but by abſtraction, <hi>&amp; actu praeciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis &amp; denudationis,</hi> and ſo by the minde you may draw them to an unity, and make a <hi>totum</hi> of them, for there is a foundation layd in the individuals for ſuch an abſtraction, but no formal general nature or unity; you muſt diveſt them of their exiſtence, and individuality firſt. There is not <hi>Ens,</hi> or <hi>ſubſtantia,</hi> or <hi>corpus,</hi> or <hi>animal in genere,</hi> or general conſideration exiſting in any one man, or in all of them, but as they are abſtracted. <hi>Plato non eſt homo in genere</hi> &amp;c. Put many ſticks together, and you may make a faggot or cart-load of them, but not make wood <hi>in genere,</hi> yea,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170879:11"/>
put all the wood in the world together, and you may make a great heap and integral of them, but you cannot make wood <hi>in genere,</hi> but by mental abſtraction, and that a man may do from a little as well as a great deal. <hi>Genus</hi> is another thing then all the individuals gathered together. <hi>Genus</hi> is not by conjunction, appoſition, or aggregation, but by abſtraction. <hi>Peter</hi> or <hi>Paul</hi> may ſay, this is my entity, my ſubſtance, my body, mine animal, my humanity, as well as my <hi>Petriety,</hi> or my <hi>Pauliety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true a man may abſtract, and as it were cut out a <hi>genus</hi> or general nature out of the individuals, and conſider that alone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a foundation for it, and a potentiality, ſo a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man when he ſeeth a piece of Timber may conceive in his mind, that if ſuch and ſuch parts were hewen and plained or carved a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, there would be an Image of the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> or a crucifix, &amp;c. yet no man wil ſay that there are any ſuch exiſting Images there, for then it were fit to be burnt. So the Chimiſt ſaith, that <hi>Sal, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> are in every thing, and boaſteth that he can extract hony out of <hi>album graekum,</hi> but they are not formally there, but may poſſibly be extracted by the diſſolution of thoſe things; ſo by mental diſſolution or abſtraction a man may fetch a <hi>genus</hi> or general out of individuals, but it is not formally in them. It ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be denyed but the object of the underſtanding pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth the act of it, but it never findeth it exiſting, but it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by an individual, and to draw forth the general nature, the underſtanding pareth off the contracting differences by ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, preciſion, or denudation. <hi>Apprehenduntur univerſalia, non apprehenſis ullis particularium differentiis. Fonſec. Metaphyſ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I conceive that there is a great difference between <hi>animal genus</hi> and <hi>animal in genere,</hi> between an exiſting <hi>genus</hi> and that thing conſidered <hi>in genere.</hi> The individual <hi>animal</hi> exiſteth, but <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal in genere</hi> exiſteth not but in the underſtanding. There is exiſtence in every thing, but where dwells exiſtence <hi>in genere?</hi> Concretes exiſt, but where do abſtracts exiſt? I will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend whether univerſals be <hi>entia realia,</hi> or <hi>entia rationis,</hi> becauſe there is a foundation for them <hi>in ente reali,</hi> but they are not formally one but by abſtraction.</p>
            <p>Indeed in reference to other <hi>genus's</hi> a <hi>genus</hi> is capable of nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical unity; <hi>Ens</hi> is one <hi>genus,</hi> and ſubſtance is one <hi>genus</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170879:12"/>
but in reference to particulars exiſting under them, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay there is one <hi>genus</hi> in <hi>Socrates,</hi> and another in <hi>Plato,</hi> for numerical unity in the ſtricteſt ſenſe is proper to individuals as integrals.</p>
            <p>But I will not contend with M. <hi>Stone</hi> about theſe notions of exiſting or extracted <hi>genus's,</hi> I ſhall leave it to younger heads which have been more lately verſed in thoſe ſtudies. But if you take <hi>genus,</hi> for the exiſting <hi>phyſical, political, mathematical,</hi> or <hi>arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial genus's</hi> as M. <hi>Stone</hi> doth, then it is impoſſible to deny any thing in the world to be a <hi>genus,</hi> for it is of one kinde or other. And by that notion every integral is nothing elſe but a <hi>cluſter</hi> of <hi>genus's</hi> bound together by the laſt individual form: and ſo we may make every thing not onely a <hi>genus,</hi> but a heap of <hi>genus's;</hi> and ſo a man hath more <hi>genus's</hi> in him, then he hath limbs, ſences, and faculties. For there is <hi>Ens,</hi> ſubſtance, body, vivens, and animal beſides humanity: and then every limb, and ſenſe, and faculty, have limb, and ſenſe, and faculty kinde in it.</p>
            <p>There is head kinde, and foot kinde, and arm kinde, and leg kinde, &amp;c. and after his conſtitution, he is dreſſed up with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>genus's</hi> from head to foot. And by the like reaſoning every thing ſhould be as full of <hi>genus's</hi> as ever it can hold. <hi>M. Stone</hi> could not think that I did deny this ſort of <hi>genus</hi> to be in the univerſal Church, for I clearly expreſſed ſo much <hi>Vind. p.</hi> 82. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Indeed if you conſider this ſociety or religion, it is a diſtinct kinde in regard of the Authour, laws, qualifications of mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, but in reference to its members, it is an integral. If this be all that is meant by <hi>totum genericum exiſtens</hi> it may paſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any dammage to this queſtion. So the ſeveral companies in <hi>London</hi> are diſtinct from other companies, yet in reference to their own members they are integrals, and in reference to the whole City they are parts, <hi>i. e.</hi> members.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But all this diſpute on which ſide ſoever it be caſt, hurts not my queſtion at all, though it may ſeem to ſtrike at this Chapter of arguments, which were taken from grounds which were gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him againſt whom I then argued, we both by <hi>genus</hi> meant a thing <hi>in genere,</hi> or <hi>general conſideration,</hi> and to that ſenſe I fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med my arguments, and then comes M. <hi>Stone</hi> and diſputes from an exiſting <hi>genus in actu exercito,</hi> that hath neither the <hi>genus</hi> nor
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170879:12"/>
               <hi>form</hi> of a <hi>genus</hi> in it, and he ſtrikes at my aguments by that which is not <hi>ad idem.</hi> If M. <hi>Ellis</hi>'s <hi>genus</hi> and M. <hi>Stones</hi> were put into a ſyllogiſm, there would be four terms, for they are not the ſame, and had I argued with M. <hi>Ellis</hi> from an exiſting <hi>integral genus,</hi> he would have thought me wilde. And therefore this is but a <hi>logo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machy</hi> about the word <hi>genus,</hi> one takes it in one ſenſe, and the other in another. I clearly layd down my meaning in the explication of the queſtion: for <hi>chap</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3. I gave different ſenſes of Catholick or general. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Firſt, the Orthodox Churches were called catholick Churches. Secondly, the Patriarchs Vicar general was called catholick. Thirdly, Catholick is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a logical ſecond notion abſtracted by the minde, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending diverſe different <hi>ſpecies</hi> under it (in which ſenſe M. <hi>Ellis</hi> took it.) Fourthly it is taken in the ſame ſenſe that we uſe to take Oecumenical, and I took the latter ſenſe, and therefore put Oecumenical into the terms of the queſtion: and ſaid there, that in the queſtion in my ſenſe the Church-catholick exiſting on earth at the ſame time is compared with particular Churches exiſting at the ſame time alſo, <hi>pag.</hi> 11. 12.</q> And in denying this Catholick Church to be a <hi>genus,</hi> I took <hi>genus</hi> in the third ſenſe as M. <hi>Ellis</hi> did.</p>
            <p>And I ſhall a little more plainly ſet it down now. The que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, Whether the whole company of viſible believers in the whole world, which is the one viſible Kingdom of Chriſt on earth, and is uſually called the Catholick or univerſal Church, being conſidered in reſpect of the particular viſible believers in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Nations, Towns, or Congregations, be the <hi>genus</hi> of them, or a great integral whereof they are but members. Here was the hinge of the queſtion handled in this chapter. And the thing that made the doubt was the diverſity of the uſe and ſignification of general and particular. For ſomtime general refers to <hi>ſpecies</hi> and particulars under it, and then it is called <hi>genus,</hi> or that thing <hi>in genere.</hi> And ſomtime general is taken for a large integral, as when we ſpeak of a general Court in a Corporation, and a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſummons, a general meeting, a general muſter, a general humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, a general pardon, our general calling, a general Covenant, the general judgment, &amp;c. Theſe phraſes are not meant of theſe things <hi>in genere,</hi> for they are ſo many individuals, but in reſpect of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170879:13"/>
the extent of the ſubject or object of them. And you may as well make the general Covenant a <hi>genus</hi> or Covenant <hi>in genere,</hi> as the generall Church to be a <hi>genus</hi> or Church <hi>in genere.</hi> It is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the general Covenant, not becauſe it is Covenant <hi>in genere,</hi> but becauſe it reacheth all the members of the Church, and they are entred into it; and ſo the univerſal Church is called general, not becauſe it is Church <hi>in genere,</hi> but becauſe it is made up of all that are entred into that general Covenant, in the whole world. So that as the general Covenant is one individual Covenant, ſo the generall or univerſall Church is one individual Church or ſociety, whereof particular Congregations contain but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells of the members.</p>
            <p>And ſomtimes particular relates to a general, as a particular man, a particular horſe, to man or horſe <hi>in genere,</hi> or the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral nature of them; and in this ſenſe it is true, <hi>Omne particulare habet ſuum generale.</hi> But ſomtime it relates to an integral, and ſignifieth a member; as a particular room in a houſe, a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſtreet in a Town, a particular ward in a City, a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar drop in a meaſure, a particular ſand in a heap, a particular man in a Town or Family. And ſo we ſay the particulars in a bill, or ſum, or bundle, ſo many, and then ſum up all in general ſo much: the particular Brigades or Regiments in an Army ſo many, and then caſt up the Army in general ſo many. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all the viſible believers in the world, both Officers and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtians are called the generall, and in that ſenſe the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall and Catholick Church, and thoſe that live in ſeverall Countries or Congregations are called particular Churches; the queſtion is whether general or univerſal as it is given to the whole Church or political Kingdom of Chriſt on earth ſignifieth a <hi>genus</hi> or Church <hi>in genere,</hi> or an integral: and whether the particular Churches are to be accounted <hi>ſpecies</hi> of that general, or members of that integral.</p>
            <p>But then coms M. <hi>Stone</hi> and neither affirms nor denieth the whole viſible Church to be either a <hi>genus</hi> or general, or an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gral; nor the particular Churches to be either <hi>ſpecies</hi> or mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, but ſtarts a new hare, and ſaith, that a Congregational Church is a Catholick Church. That is to ſay, as I conceive, becauſe every particular Church is a Congregationall Church,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170879:13"/>
and Congregational Church may be predicated of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church, therefore Congregational Church is the <hi>genus</hi> of them all. He dared not make the whole Church to be a <hi>genus</hi> of the particular Churches, and he would not make it the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gral.</p>
            <p>And whereas I had proved <hi>chap.</hi> 2. that there is an univerſal viſible Church, and that it is one, I expected that either it ſhould have been denyed that there is ſuch an univerſal Church, or that it is one, or if it be one, then to have it declared whether it be one generically, or one integrally and numerically; but M. <hi>Stone</hi> waves them both, and ſaith, a Congregational Church is a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, and ſo puts a ſurreptitions queſtion in the room of it. Whereby he doth implicitely grant what I affirmed, that the whole univerſal Church is not the <hi>genus</hi> of the particular Congregationall Churches, but Church <hi>in genere</hi> or generall notion.</p>
            <p>It is true if we refer a ſtreet, or ward in a City, or a Brigade or Regiment in an Army, to Street, Ward, Brigade or Regiment <hi>in genere,</hi> they are particulars under ſuch generals; but if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to the City or Army whereof they are parts, ſo they are members. So if we refer particular Congregations to Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations <hi>in genere,</hi> they are particulars; or, if you will have it ſo, <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or individuals rather of Congregations <hi>in genere,</hi> but if we refer them to the whole Church they are members thereof. And it cannot be denyed but particular Congregations may, yea muſt bear relation unto both.</p>
            <p>And by the ſame way of reaſoning that he makes a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Church to be a Catholick Church, a man may make a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church an individual Church, a Church that is one nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merically to be a Catholick Church, for all theſe may be predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated of every Congregational Church, and that eſſentially as they are ſuch. And ſo a man may ſay an individual man is a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick man, an individual horſe a catholick horſe, an indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual houſe a catholick houſe, an individual eye a catholick eye, an individual foot a catholick foot, becauſe individual may be predicated of all theſe, and that eſſentially as ſuch. And ſo we may make <hi>hic homo</hi> to be the <hi>genus</hi> of all the men in the world, becauſe it may be predicated of every man. And ſo we may ſet
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170879:14"/>
individual, and <hi>unum numero</hi> above <hi>Ens</hi> the higheſt <hi>genus</hi> of all, becauſe every <hi>Ens</hi> is individual and <hi>unum numero,</hi> if it doth exiſt. And ſo <hi>genus</hi> ſhall be a pretty <hi>Proteus. Omnia transformat ſeſe in miracula rerum.</hi> And every man ſhal be an individual particular general Catholick man.</p>
            <p>There is a ſecond thing about which M. <hi>Stone</hi> beſtoweth much pains in his book to invalidate this chapter, and that is to prove that <hi>individua</hi> are <hi>ſpecies.</hi> I am not willing to contend with him about the <hi>logomachy,</hi> and the rather becauſe though it croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſomething ſaid in this chapter, yet it invalidates not the cauſe at all.</p>
            <p>That there is an eſſential predication of that which Logicians call <hi>ſpecies infima,</hi> and he <hi>genus infimum</hi> upon the individuals, ſo that it doth the office of a <hi>genus</hi> thereunto cannot be denied, and therefore as it reſpects the individuals it is called <hi>ſpecies praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis,</hi> as the other, as they reſpect the ſuperiour <hi>genus</hi> are called <hi>ſpecies ſubjicibilis, Burgerſd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Logicians carrying the name <hi>ſpecies</hi> no lower then ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract natures which have ſome univerſality in them, though the loweſt that may be and neereſt individuals, did not account indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduals to be <hi>ſpecies,</hi> for though univerſals may be diſtributed lower and lower into leſs univerſals; yet are not, in their opinion diſtributed into <hi>ſpecies ſingulares,</hi> or into ſeveral integrals, which are a <hi>totum</hi> of another oppoſite nature. But they conceive <hi>genus</hi> to be <hi>natura univerſalior ſub quâ alia minùs univerſalis continetur Keckerm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>ſpecies</hi> to be <hi>natura univerſalis alteri univerſaliori ſubjecta:</hi> and the loweſt <hi>ſpecies</hi> to be that which hath obtained the loweſt and utmoſt perfection among the univerſals <hi>ultimum univerſalium.</hi> And indeed there is a difference between <hi>ſpecies</hi> and <hi>individuum. Quamvis ſpecies conſervari poteſt in uno individuo, genus tamen non potest conſervari in una ſpecie, Burgerſd.</hi> 45. So that as M. <hi>Stone</hi> confeſſeth that <hi>animal</hi> was not a compleat <hi>genus</hi> untill man was made, yet man was compleat as ſoon as <hi>Adam</hi> was made.</p>
            <p>Again, they ſay that <hi>ſpecies <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> perfectior eſt genere, ſed individuum non eſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> perfectius ſua ſpecie, i. e.</hi> man is more perfect in regard of eſſence then animal, that is, hath a further perfection added to him then was in animal, yet <hi>Socrates</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170879:14"/>
is not more perfect in eſſence then man in general. The <hi>ſpecies</hi> hath the integral nature of the <hi>genus,</hi> and beſides that it hath an eſſential difference perfecting it, and thruſting it on a degree fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but the individual hath no ſuch eſſential difference added to the loweſt <hi>ſpecies</hi> to perfect that, or thruſt it on further, but the <hi>ſpecies eſſentiam ejus abſolvit;</hi> it hath nothing but individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality and exiſtence added, whereby it becomes an integral; there is no eſſential perfecting part found in one that is not found in another, but only the ſoul and body of <hi>Peter</hi> is not the ſoul and body of <hi>Paul.</hi> And for ought I know he may make the animal, ſubſtance, and <hi>Ens</hi> in <hi>Peter,</hi> differ as much from the <hi>animal,</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and <hi>Ens</hi> in Paul, as the humane nature in <hi>Peter</hi> from that which is in <hi>Paul,</hi> ſeeing they are all alike under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, as well as the humane nature, and ſo make ſeveral <hi>ſpecies</hi> of them alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Genus</hi> is like a Bell that ringeth out, and ſtrikes on both ſides, and ſo <hi>Ens</hi> or being in general ſtrikes double, it is either <hi>primum, vel à primo ortum; à primo ortum</hi> is double, <hi>ſubſtantia, vel acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens; ſubſtantia</hi> is double, <hi>corporea, vel incorporea ſive ſpiritualis; corporea</hi> is double, <hi>ſimplex, vel miſta; miſta</hi> is double, <hi>vivens, non vivens; vivens</hi> is double, <hi>vegetativa, vel ſenſitiva; ſenſitiva</hi> is double, <hi>homo, vel brutum;</hi> and then you are fallen as low as uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſals go, which the Logicians commonly make the loweſt <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies;</hi> and then the Bell, as it were falls into a ſingle touling of individuals, which are ſtroaks of the ſame ſide, and man ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Peter, Paul, John, Robert;</hi> ſo that the peal of <hi>genus's</hi> that ſtruck double before, at laſt when they are fallen as low as they can fall into a ſingle chime, ſtrokes on the ſame ſide: and indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duals differ no more from one another, then ſingle ſtrokes of the Bell one from another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Genus</hi> bears twinns which are oppoſite, nay contrary one to the other, and ſo ſtruggle in the womb, like <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> of two contrary natures, hairy and ſmooth, but the loweſt <hi>ſpecies</hi> beareth only ſingle Children of the ſame nature.</p>
            <p>If a man in his mind travells from <hi>Ens</hi> or being which is the higheſt <hi>genus,</hi> he finds it divide preſently into two oppoſite ways, one as it were on the right hand, the other on the left, <hi>viz,</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170879:15"/>
and accident; if he will trace the one way <hi>viz.</hi> ſubſtance, he findes it preſently divided again into two oppoſite ways, <hi>viz.</hi> Corporeal, Spiritual; if he traceth Corporeal, he findes it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide again immediately into ſimple, and mixt; if he traceth mixt, he findes it divide into that which hath life, and that which hath none; if he traceth that which hath life, it divideth imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately into vegetative and ſenſitive; if he traceth ſenſitive, it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videth immediately into man and brute, now if he will trace man, he findes him no more to divide as the former into oppoſite perfecting differences, thruſting that nature on further, but he goes on from generation to generation, ſtill the ſame in kinde and eſſence, like a right on path, that goes further and further, but divideth not into croſs paths. Or to make the ſimilitude more full, it leadeth him out into a plain or heath where are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ways to ride a breſt in, but they all come from the ſame head, and lead to the ſame town: and theſe are the individuals which proceed from the loweſt <hi>ſpecies,</hi> but divide not into lower differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perfecting <hi>ſpecies.</hi> So that though they agree with other <hi>ſpecies,</hi> in that they are comprehended by ſomething more general, and that is predicated on them, yet they are not predicated upon any inferiours; they may be cut in pieces into members, but not diſtributed into further perfecting diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eſſential forms.</p>
            <p>So that call individuals, <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or what you will, yet you ſee they are not like other <hi>ſpecies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to prove them to be <hi>ſpecies,</hi> M. <hi>Stone</hi> makes them not <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa quae ſolâ ratione diſſentiunt, i. e.</hi> though all men have humane nature, yet they are not the ſame: But <hi>oppoſita quae re &amp; ratione diſſentiunt.</hi> And truly if it were ever true of men, it is true in our age, where almoſt every man is oppoſite to each other; <hi>Quot homines, tot ſententiae.</hi> But this is not an eſſential but accidental oppoſition. And though he cannot make them contraries, <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum unum uni opponitur,</hi> yet he makes them <hi>Diſparata, Quorum u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num multis pariter opponitur.</hi> By reaſon of their diſtinct forms and eſſences: well, be it ſo, but then he muſt make two or three kindes of <hi>Diſparata.</hi> For formerly we were wont to account things that are under divers <hi>genus's</hi> to be <hi>diſparata,</hi> as <hi>homo, arbor, lapis:</hi> or intermediate different <hi>ſpecies</hi> under the ſame <hi>genus,</hi> as yellow,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170879:15"/>
blew, green, red, under colour, as M. <hi>Stone</hi> acknowledgeth, <hi>p.</hi> 26. But by this opinion the ſeveral yellows, blews, greens, and reds, are each of <hi>diſparata</hi> to themſelves, and ſo are oppoſite to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves though dyed in the ſame fatt at the ſame time. And by the ſame reaſon he may ſay that every thred of a cloth both warp and woof of the ſame cloth are oppoſite colours, and every <hi>pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum</hi> of every one of thoſe threds are of an oppoſite colour. I ſhould rather have ſaid that they are <hi>ſimilia,</hi> and that <hi>unum multis pariter aſſimilatur, potius quam opponitur.</hi> But I ſhall let him enjoy his notion, becauſe it hurteth me not. He yieldeth the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of this opinion <hi>p.</hi> 23. that there are ſo many <hi>ſpecies</hi> of water, wine, or milk, as there are drops of them in the whole world; and ſo a hundred thouſand <hi>ſpecies</hi> of water in a pail full of water, and theſe have all oppoſite eſſential forms, and yet are ſimilar; which is as much as to ſay, they have ſimilar, oppoſite eſſential forms, <hi>Gravia bella fratrum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what if the individuals be <hi>ſpecies,</hi> yea ſo many <hi>genus's,</hi> yea comprehend a bundle of <hi>genus's</hi> in the belly of every one of them, as by this Logick they muſt. Will this be any hinderance that many of theſe individuals may be brought into one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegral?</p>
            <p>Suppoſe every brick hath brick-kinde, and body-kinde, and ſubſtance-kinde, and <hi>Ens</hi>-kinde in it; yet may not an hundred thouſand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bricks make one brick-houſe; and a hundred thouſand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake one tiled roof; and a thouſand pieces of timber make one timber-houſe; and many individual men be in one family, one town, one army, one Kingdom, or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth? So may many individual viſible believers be in one Congregation, and many Congregations of them bee in one Claſſis, and many Claſſis in one Province, and many Provinces be in one Nation.</p>
            <p>And all the Chriſtian Nations in the world be one univerſal viſible Church, and that be an integral.</p>
            <p>When the firſt Goſpel-Church (which might be called general or Catholick in contradiſtinction to the National Church of the Jews; and becauſe then the partition wal between Jew and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile was broken down, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion iſſued forth for teaching all Nations and baptizing them) grew too big to meet in one
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170879:16"/>
place for all Ordinances, it divided it ſelf into many leſs Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, called, though improperly and at ſecond hand, Churches, yet then this diviſion was of an integral into its members, not of a <hi>genus</hi> or general into its <hi>ſpecies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I acknowledge the matter of the viſible Church militant uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, or viſible Kingdom of Chriſt on earth, to be the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar viſible believers, and the external form thereof to be their joint ſubmitting unto Chriſt's regiment and laws under his Officers where they dwell, but this whole Church when it comes to bee divided, it is conſidered according to the places where thoſe members dwell, either in <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> or <hi>New-England,</hi> &amp;c, and ſo receive particular denomination from thoſe places; but this diviſion is of an integral into its members, as the parts reſpect the whole, and of adjuncts into their ſubject places if they be conſidered in reference to the places wherein they are contained.</p>
            <p>Look at the Church <hi>in geneſi,</hi> ſaith M. <hi>Cawdrey, vindic. vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciarum,</hi> 72. and the ſingle members are the cauſes thereof as an integral, but look on it <hi>in analyſi,</hi> in the diſtribution of it into Congregations, and ſo it giveth eſſence unto them, and they are parcells of that greater integral. Though in the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an integral the parts are before the whole, as the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial cauſes thereof, yet in the diſtribution the whole is before the parts, <hi>Cawd. p.</hi> 82.</p>
            <p>And whereas I had proved that the univerſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is not a <hi>genus</hi> or Church <hi>in genere,</hi> becauſe it doth exiſt, or hath an indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual exiſtence of its own, which a thing <hi>in genere</hi> hath not, <hi>vind. p.</hi> 79. <hi>l.</hi> 8. To this argument M. <hi>Stone</hi> anſwers, by affirming that <hi>genus</hi> doth exiſt. But when he comes to prove it, he proves only that the integral nature of the <hi>genus</hi> doth exiſt in the indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duals, and leaves us from them to abſtract the <hi>genus,</hi> which is an univerſal, but proves not that the univerſal doth exiſt any where, but in the mind of man, or Angel. Now as it doth exiſt in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral individuals, it is contracted, and is an integral, and muſt be looſed from his contraction by abſtraction, before it can be a logical <hi>genus,</hi> or that thing conſidered <hi>in genere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is as if he ſhould ſay, as it is an integeal it is a <hi>genus,</hi> which he confeſſeth differs very much. There is that which may be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170879:16"/>
but it doth not exiſt as abſtracted but as contracted. So I may in my minde conſider a priſoner that is bound with many chains, without his chains, and ſo a free-man, but I dare not ſay he exiſteth a free-man. I can abſtract a man from his riches, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, piety, nobility, that is endued with them, but I cannot ſay he exiſteth ſo. Where a thing <hi>in genere,</hi> or general notion, or general conſideration doth exiſt, but in the underſtanding, I, as yet know not.</p>
            <p>Moreover as ſuch a nature doth exiſt in individuals, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold, but as I have abſtracted it, it is but one. As it doth exiſt in individuals each differ from other (as M. <hi>Stone</hi> acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) <hi>ne &amp; ratione,</hi> and by his own Logick all thoſe individuals are oppoſites, and ſo diſſentanies, now <hi>diſſentaneum eſt quod à re diſſentit,</hi> but one is not a <hi>diſſentanie,</hi> much leſs an oppoſite to itſelf. Now <hi>genus</hi> is one, becauſe it is <hi>totum quod habet partes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore you muſt diveſt it of exiſtency, before you can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it as a <hi>genus,</hi> or general, or thing <hi>in genere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to apply it to the whole Church in reference to the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it: the whole Church hath an exiſtence of its own, as an integral, being <hi>individuum,</hi> as <hi>Ames</hi> confeſſeth, but as M. <hi>Stone's genus</hi> hath no exiſtence, but in the <hi>ſpecies.</hi> The exiſtence of the whole Church reſulteth from the conjoined exiſtence of the members, but the exiſtence of a <hi>genus</hi> is abſtracted from the <hi>ſpecies.</hi> The whole Oecumenical viſible Church hath no <hi>ſpecies</hi> or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual Churches under it, whereof it's the <hi>genus;</hi> but is made up of individual viſible believers, and then divided into ſeveral pieces or parcell, which we call particular Congregations Like a piece of ice divided or marked out into many little pieces; the great piece of ice is not the <hi>genus</hi> of them, but the integral, and they are the members. Though the whole Ocean were frozen it would make but a great integral, and the ſeveral parcels thereof mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
            <p>But it would not be the <hi>genus</hi> of thoſe parcells, for ice <hi>in genere</hi> is the <hi>genus.</hi> A pail of water is not the <hi>genus</hi> of the ſeveral drops that are in it, but is an integral, and they are members, but water <hi>in genere</hi> is the <hi>genus.</hi> A heap of ſand (though there were no more ſand in the world but that) is not the <hi>genus</hi> of the particular ſands in it, but ſand <hi>in genere.</hi> So the univerſal Church is not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170879:17"/>
the <hi>genus</hi> of particular believers, but believer <hi>in genere,</hi> nor of the particular Congregations, but Congregation <hi>in genere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas I had ſaid in my ſecond Argument <hi>vind. p.</hi> 79. <hi>l.</hi> 30. that <hi>Quod habet partes extra partes eſt totum integrale.</hi> M. <hi>Stone</hi> denies it to be a true definition. I anſwer I had it out of <hi>Burgerſdicius p.</hi> 47. and I conceive he defines it ſo in oppoſition to that which he calls <hi>totum eſſentiale, quod conſtat ex materiâ &amp; formâ,</hi> for there the parts do <hi>mutuo ſe pervadere, &amp; loco, &amp; ſitu non differunt,</hi> as the ſoul and body in man, but the parts of an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gral <hi>quâ</hi> integral do differ in both. But to make the Argument paſt his exceptions, I ſhall change onely one word, and in that change only expreſs <hi>Burgerſd.</hi> his meaning more clearly. <hi>Quod habet membra extra membra eſt totum integrale, ſed eccleſia univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalis viſibilis habet,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ergo.</hi> The univerſal Church hath its members one diſtinct and ſeveral beſide and without each other, whether you conſider them to be particular believers, which are the prime members, or Congregations, &amp;c. which are ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary.</p>
            <p>And whereas I had ſaid in my third Argument that the whole Church is made up of the viſible believers in particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and of ſuch as are not fixed members in any particular Congregation, <hi>vind. p.</hi> 80. <hi>l.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Stone</hi> anſwereth, That individual Chriſtians which are not members of any particular Congregation, are not formally po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical Church-members. Now if by political Church-members he means actual members of this or that particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is true, but they are political members of the Church-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick viſible, for they have taken Chriſt to be their King, and his laws to rule them, they are enrowled by baptiſme, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on Chriſts Ordinances, and ſubject themſelves to his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, where they become, though ſome occaſion may not ſuffer them to be fixed in a particular Congregation. They are poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical members of Chriſts viſible Kingdom primarily, by being members of the Church-Catholick, the memberſhip in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregations is ſecondary, and but accidental to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. He ſaith they are members <hi>materialiter non formaliter,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not confederate. But I anſwer, they are confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate <hi>i. e.</hi> in Covenant with Chriſt the head and King of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170879:17"/>
Church, and confederate with the members in the general Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, into which they are entred, and any other Covenant or confederation to conſtitute a political Church-member I finde none in Scripture, neither ſcrip nor ſcrawl. And I conceive all Congregational confederations and Congregations, to be but accidental to the univerſal Church, by reaſon of the numeroſity of its members, for could we conceive that all the members of the whole-Church could meet in one place, and partake of the ſame numerical Ordinances orderly, the meeting in ſeveral places ſhould ceaſe.</p>
            <p>The woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> which M. <hi>Stone</hi> inſtanceth in, by being a viſible Saint and believer, though ſhe was not forma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly thereby a member of the Jewiſh Church, as he ſaith, yet was ſhe a member of the Evangelical Church, and that compleatly if ſhe were ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized, if not baptized, then but incompleatly, and <hi>materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The place which is brought by M. <hi>Stone</hi> to prove the Apoſtles to be fixed members of the particular Church in <hi>Jeruſalem; Act.</hi> 1.2.3.13.14. proves it not, but onely that they abode in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> untill the coming down of the holy Ghoſt at Pentecoſt, to inable them to diſcharge their Apoſtleſhips, but then they travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led over the world, and joined in Ordinances with the Churches which they converted, as Officers adminiſtring both word and ſeals, and were no more fixed members of the Church of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> then of any other Church where they became. They were never dwellers at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but men of <hi>Galilee,</hi> only ſtayd a while at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> upon occaſion.</p>
            <p>And whereas I ſayd in my fourth Argument, that the Church univerſal is not <hi>genus,</hi> or Church <hi>in genere,</hi> becauſ it hath accidents and adjuncts exiſting in it as its own, <hi>vind. p.</hi> 80. <hi>l.</hi> 28.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Stone</hi> affirmeth that a <hi>genus</hi> is capable of inherent accidents as its own, <hi>p.</hi> 35. and more largely <hi>p.</hi> 21. with a wonder at me for that opinion. But I muſt cleave to mine opinion, as I meant it, for all that he hath ſayd againſt it. For I have proved that we muſt diveſt the integral of the <hi>genus</hi> from its exiſtence, before it can be a <hi>genus</hi> or thing <hi>in genere,</hi> and diveſting it of exiſtence we muſt neceſſarily diveſt its adjuncts from exiſtence alſo. Now as <hi>animal</hi> in a man furniſhed with all his adjuncts and accidents
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170879:18"/>
doth exiſt, it is <hi>integrum animal,</hi> it is not <hi>animal in genere.</hi> It is true we abſtract the proper accidents with the nature, and ſay they belong to that nature primarily, as viſibility to humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but viſibility exiſteth only in on integral man. No man e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard <hi>homo in genere</hi> laugh. And in a Logical abſtract ſenſe I granted <hi>vind. p.</hi> 106. as much as M. <hi>Stone</hi> contends for; but if <hi>homo in genere</hi> doth not exiſt, viſibility <hi>in genere</hi> doth not exiſt neither. But the Oecumenical Church is not Church <hi>in genere,</hi> neither doth M. <hi>Stone</hi> think it is Church <hi>in genere,</hi> and yet <hi>p.</hi> 35. he doth grant a Church <hi>in genere,</hi> and ſaith that the particular Churches are <hi>ſpecies</hi> of it. Now ſhould Church <hi>in genere,</hi> and Oecumenical or Catholick, or Synholick Church, as M. <hi>Stone</hi> calls it <hi>p.</hi> 40. in which ſenſe I took it, and it is uſually taken, be brought into a Syllogiſm together, there would be four terms.</p>
            <p>Again, whereas I ſaid in the proſecution of this fourth Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the univerſal Church cannot be a <hi>genus</hi> or Church <hi>in genere,</hi> becauſe it is capable of being <hi>major</hi> and <hi>minor,</hi> of greater or leſs extent, <hi>vind. p.</hi> 81. <hi>l.</hi> 11. To this M. <hi>Stone</hi> anſwers, that a <hi>genus</hi> is capable of being <hi>majus</hi> and <hi>minus in actu exercito.</hi> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind is capable of increaſe, virtue ſhal increaſe at the calling of the Jews: and ſin may increaſe, becauſe the particular virtues and vices may increaſe.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, the queſtion is not about <hi>genus in actu exercito,</hi> for that properly is not <hi>genus,</hi> but an Integral under that <hi>genus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there is no more put into the definition of man then <hi>ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal rationale,</hi> now there are hundred Millions of men in the world then there was when there was but one man: ſo there is no more put into the definition of Church <hi>in genere</hi> now it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of Millions of viſible believers, then there was when it had far fewer members, the Integral is inlarged indeed, but not Church <hi>in genere.</hi> Though a Giant be <hi>major homo,</hi> yet he is not <hi>magis homo,</hi> and though a dwarf be <hi>minor homo,</hi> yet he is not <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nùs homo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So for virtue and vice there is nothing more put into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition by the increaſe of them, and therefore they have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther definition then they had at the loweſt ebb; now the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion explicates the eſſence of the thing. The habits of virtue and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170879:18"/>
vice may grow ſtronger, but <hi>gradus non variant ſpeciem,</hi> they may be in more ſubjects, but that varies not the <hi>ſpecies</hi> neither. So that <hi>genus</hi> being <hi>unum, conſiſtit in indiviſibili:</hi> take away either <hi>animal</hi> or <hi>rationale</hi> and you ſpoil the definition of man: and ſo you can add nothing to the eſſence of it more then is in it, unleſs you put a further perfecting diſtinguiſhing eſſential form, and ſo make a new <hi>ſpecies</hi> below man. The majority or minority of a thing reſpects the members, and ſo is aſcribed to it as an integral; either continuous magnitude as in man or brute, or diſcreet as in <hi>ſpecies,</hi> by the multiplication of members, and this is the caſe of the whole Church, it may grow greater or leſs as the members are multiplyed or decreaſed.</p>
            <p>Alſo whereas I ſaid in the proſecution of the fourth Argument that the whole Church is not a <hi>genus,</hi> or Church <hi>in genere,</hi> becauſ it is mutable and fluxile, which are accidents of an Integral only, <hi>vind. p.</hi> 81. <hi>l.</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Stone</hi> anſwers this Argument by affirming that <hi>genus</hi> may bee mutable, <hi>Totum genus plantarum &amp; brutorum</hi> is mutable and fluxile.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that the Integrals under each of thoſe generals is mutable and fluxile, but ſtill the <hi>genus</hi> of them, or things <hi>in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere</hi> is not ſo.</p>
            <p>There is nothing taken out of the definition of it by the change or death of the individual Integrals under thoſe generals, nor nothing added by the renewal of more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> It may be objected, that in this ſenſe no Integral is mutable neither, becauſe the definition of it is not changed, though the individual Integral be changed or periſh, and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer, That every individual Integral is an example and inſtance of an Integral, and hath the definition of an Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gral belong unto it, but every individual exiſting <hi>genus,</hi> or <hi>genus in actu exercito,</hi> as M. <hi>Stone</hi> calls it, is not an example of the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> much leſs the thing <hi>in genere,</hi> for the definition of <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> cannot agree thereto, ſeeing a <hi>genus</hi> is an univerſal, and that is but particular, yea an individual of, or under that <hi>genus,</hi> and ſo is but an Integral. If any eſſential part of an exiſting Integral be changed then it is not an Integral of the ſame kinde it was,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170879:19"/>
and ſo the peculiar definition of it muſt be changed, yet ſtill it is an Integral.</p>
            <p>There cannot in propriety of ſpeech be an example of the ſame <hi>genus,</hi> becauſe it is but one, but there may be many examples of Integrals under that <hi>genus,</hi> and they indeed are mutable and flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xile, as they are Integrals that exiſt. How can an individual man be an example of <hi>genus humanum,</hi> ſince, by his own logick, it is but the loweſt <hi>ſpecies,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſpecies eſt pars generis,</hi> and <hi>pars eſt quae contine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur à toto,</hi> therefore a part cannot be the whole, nor an example of the whole. And to ſpeak properly, if you would give an exampl of a <hi>genus,</hi> you muſt give an example of an univerſal, not of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual <hi>e. g. Ens</hi> is a <hi>genus,</hi> and ſubſtance, and accident, and ſpirit, and body, and animal, &amp;c. conſidered in the general na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of them. And if you will call <hi>individuals ſpecies,</hi> then is man in general conſideration a <hi>genus,</hi> but you muſt not bring an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual man to be an example of man <hi>in genere,</hi> which is an univerſal. I ſay, an individual is no inſtance of an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, it hath integrality in it, but no univerſality. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalia ſunt perpetua quae per ſe ipſa nec gignuntur nec intereunt. Fonſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca Metaph. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 28.</p>
            <p>And whereas I had ſaid <hi>vind. p.</hi> 81. <hi>l.</hi> 36. in proſecution of the ſame Argument, that the whole Church is not a <hi>genus,</hi> or Church <hi>in genere;</hi> becauſe it is meaſured by time and place. M. <hi>Stone</hi> ſaith <hi>p.</hi> 11. that <hi>genus</hi> as well as <hi>integrum</hi> is an exiſting thing meaſured by time and place.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that the integrals of ſuch or ſuch a kinde, or under that general, are indeed meaſured by time and place; but the kind conſidered <hi>in genere</hi> is not ſo. My queſtion was, whether the whole Oecumenical Church exiſting at the ſame time, be Church <hi>in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere,</hi> or a great integral conſiſting of many members.</p>
            <p>But how particular time and place comes to take a meaſure of Church or man <hi>in genere;</hi> I as yet perceive not. As it was not drawn from the univerſal Church of one or two or ten ages, ſo it is not meaſured by them: ſo that though this or that Church ceaſeth, yea all the members of the whole Church that are now exiſting ſhould dye, and the whole Church conſiſt of new mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, yet Church <hi>in genere</hi> ceaſeth not, nei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her is altered, unleſs you will ſay that the whole time of this world takes a meaſure
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170879:19"/>
of it, becauſe it ſhall exiſt in this kinde no longer then this world endures. Though individuals under a <hi>genus</hi> be Corporeal, yet the univerſals of them <hi>non ſunt ex iis corporeis quae per ſe loco &amp; tempori ſubjecta ſunt, ut per ſeipſas digito deſignari poſſunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeca, Meta. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 28. <hi>qu.</hi> 2. They are onely individuals, and ſo Integrals that are tyed to <hi>hic &amp; nunc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas I had proved the whole Church to be an Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gral becauſe there is admiſſion into it, nutrition and edification of members in it, and ejection of members out of it, <hi>vind. p.</hi> 82. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"M. <hi>Stone</hi> ſaith <hi>p.</hi> 9. that a <hi>genus</hi> is capable of admiſſion, nutrition, and ejection. <hi>Animal</hi> admitted man and beaſt under his wing. A man at birth is admitted into mankind, ſo is a lyon and a horſe into their kind when they come into the world, and by death are excommunicated out of that kind.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, the Integrals of ſuch a kind are admitted and ejected, but not the univerſals; every Integral muſt be of, or under one kinde or other: If indeed there were a new creature made, differing in kinde from all creatures that ever were made, then were there a new <hi>genus</hi> admitted into the world, or if any of the former kindes were quite deſtroyed, then were a <hi>genus</hi> ejected indeed. But by adding the word members admitted, nouriſhed, edified, or ejected, this Argument is put beyond his exceptions: and this is the caſe of the whole Church, there are members continually admitted and edified, and ſomtime by cenſure ejected, therefore it is an Integral; for member and Integral are <hi>relata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas I ſaid in my ſixth Argument, that the whole Church militant on earth at the ſame time is not Church <hi>in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere,</hi> becauſe it is capable of Officers, and had once actual Officers over it, and hath ſtill Officers that are indefinitely and habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>i. e. in actu primo</hi> Officers to the whole, <hi>vind. p.</hi> 82. <hi>l.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"M. <hi>Stone</hi> anſwers, that a <hi>genus</hi> may be capable of Officers. Every compleat Eccleſiaſtical ſociety or Church is furniſhed with Officers; But <hi>Boſton</hi> Congregation is a compleat entire Church, or a compleat Eccleſiaſtical ſociety; therefore <hi>Boſton</hi> Church is furniſhed with Officers, <hi>p.</hi> 36. <hi>And this be endeavours to make out, p.</hi> 33. And there he tells us, that an individual Church is a <hi>ſpecies,</hi> as it reſpects Church <hi>in genere</hi> under which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170879:20"/>
it is comprehended, and yet as it contains members it is an Integral.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"Hence it is that every individual Church contains members, becauſe it is an <hi>integrum,</hi> and yet it is a <hi>ſpecies</hi> as it ſtands in reference to a Church <hi>in genere.</hi> Hence alſo a Church <hi>in genere</hi> may be ſaid to have members and Officers in it, not conſidered under the nature of <hi>genus,</hi> but becauſe the <hi>ſpecies ſpecialiſſima</hi> containeth members, it is an <hi>Integrum.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas I had ſaid a <hi>genus</hi> is not capable of Officers, he anſwers: <q rend="inline margQuotes">"It is true <hi>in actu ſignato,</hi> but that which is <hi>genus</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the <hi>ſpecies</hi> and individuals which contains mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, may in that reſpect be ſaid to comprehend members and Officers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I am glad to ſee M. <hi>Stone</hi> at length finde out the notion of a Church <hi>in genere,</hi> a Vine <hi>in genere,</hi> a body <hi>in genere;</hi> I hope it may prove a clew to help us out of this Labyrinth. But how doth this vine <hi>in genere</hi> give eſſence to the individual vines, or this Church <hi>in genere</hi> give eſſence to the particulars, or this body <hi>in genere</hi> give eſſence to the individuals? Surely not by generation (except by generation <hi>in genere</hi> alſo) but becauſe the entire nature exiſting in an individual vine, Church, body, giveth eſſence to it; ſo that it will follow, that the entire Integral exiſting nature comprehended under theſe kindes gives eſſence to the individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and not thoſe natures in general conſideration, or <hi>in genere.</hi> And therefore either <hi>Ramus</hi> hath not given us a right definition of <hi>genus</hi> (as ſome better Logicians then I conceive) or elſe he giveth a definition only of an exiſting integral nature of a <hi>genus,</hi> which is onely an Integral of or under ſuch a <hi>genus,</hi> and ſo hath paſſed by the topick of a thing <hi>in genere,</hi> or general conſideration <hi>in abſtracto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then I argue, that if that which is <hi>genus</hi> comprehends the <hi>ſpecies</hi> and individuals which contain members, may in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect be ſaid to comprehend members and Officers, then the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and <hi>integrum</hi> are all one; for the <hi>genus</hi> hath members, yea, principal members, even Officers as well as <hi>integrum,</hi> ſaith he. But here M. <hi>Stone</hi> helpeth himſelf with a diſtinction, and ſaith, this is not as conſidered under the nature of a <hi>genus,</hi> but becauſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170879:20"/>
the <hi>ſpecies ſpecialiſſima</hi> contains members as it is an <hi>integrum.</hi> And I deſire to make uſe of the ſame diſtinction alſo, and ſay, that the Officers are not Officers of it as it is a <hi>genus,</hi> or as it is conſidered <hi>in genere,</hi> but as it is an <hi>integrum</hi> under ſuch a <hi>genus.</hi> And ſo let me ſtrengthen all my former Arguments againſt which he hath ſo much excepted, by his own diſtinction, and ſay, that the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence of the whole Church, the having <hi>membra extra membra,</hi> the having exiſting accidents, the being <hi>majus</hi> &amp; <hi>minus,</hi> the being mutable &amp; fluxile, the being meaſured by time and place, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, nutrition, edification, and ejection of members, and the doing, actions, and operations, betide to the whole Church, not as conſidered under the notion of a <hi>genus</hi> or Church <hi>in genere,</hi> but becauſe it is an <hi>individuum,</hi> and ſo an <hi>integrum</hi> under ſuch a <hi>genus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame exiſting thing being conſidered in ſeveral reſpects, may be a cauſe, an effect, a ſubject, an adjunct, a conſent any, a diſſentany, an <hi>integrum,</hi> and a <hi>genus</hi> in M. <hi>Stone's</hi> ſenſe, <hi>in actu exercito,</hi> but it cannot be that thing <hi>in genere.</hi> The whole univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church in reference to ſociety or polity in general is a <hi>ſpecies</hi> or individual, but in reference to its members both private and publick, it is an <hi>integrum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before he leaves this Argument, he adds a ſuppliment to make his anſwer full, <hi>pag.</hi> 36. <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"That there are no ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall Officers in the Church, all Officers in the Church are actual, habitual Officers are <hi>non ens poſſibile, quod non eſt, ſed poteſt eſſe.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, that they are all actual Officers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and might, if they were able and had a call, officiate in any part of the Church; and do actually ſerve the whole Church, by admitting members into it, and watching over a company of the members of it in their own places, and adminiſtring Word and Seals in many Congregations, yea Counties, and ſomtimes many Nations, but exert not the exerciſe of their power to the extent of the whole Church actually, in every part of their office.</p>
            <p>So Juſtices of the Peace for the County do not ordinarily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute their Office in every Town of the County, and yet have power by their Commiſſion, if they could do it, and had a call thereto. But as watch-men in particular wards do ſafe-guard
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170879:21"/>
the whole City as well as their particular wards, though they ſtand not in every part of the City, and are called the City watch-men; ſo do Chriſts Miniſters ſerve the whole Church in their particular places, though they cannot reſide, or act in every place of the whole Church, but could do it in regard of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of their office and commiſſion, if they had ability of body and minde, &amp; a cal or opportunity. I mean not by habitual power that which is never drawn into act, but the power in one officer is not drawn into act in every part of the Church, nor in every part of the exerciſe of his office. And the lett is not any want of power by their office, but want of ability in themſelvs, and of call and opportunity in the ſeverall places. And ſo they divide that full execution of their office among the officers, and ſpiritual watch-men of this City of God, and ſome take care of ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and members of the whole Church, and others of other actually, for order and covenience ſake, and their better edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>And whereas I had ſaid in my ſeventh argument <hi>vind. p.</hi> 84. <hi>l.</hi> 8. That the whole Church is an integrall, becauſe it hath actions and operations of its own, for a thing conſidered <hi>in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere</hi> is not capable thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"To this M. <hi>Stone</hi> anſwers, that a <hi>genus</hi> is capable of actions and operations of its own, becauſe <hi>operatio ſequitur eſſe, &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ens agit.</hi> A <hi>genus</hi> hath properties and qualities, and therefore can act; where there is no <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> there can be no <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but that is the end of all being <hi>p.</hi> 21. 22. It is true <hi>ſaith he,</hi> the Church-Catholick hath actions and operations of its own; and that it exiſts and acts its individualls, yet his properties are his own, and ſo likewiſe are his operations. <hi>p.</hi> 36.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, that theſe actions and operations are properly the operations of the integrall under that <hi>genus.</hi> Now becauſe all the integralls of that kind have thoſe operations, therefore they are attributed in notion to that <hi>genus,</hi> and ſaid to belong there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but that thing <hi>in genere</hi> opperates not, but in the individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls or integrals under it. But the whole Church may, as I there proved, act in one and the ſame individuall act, as a City or Kingdome may do, therefore it is one integrall. A <hi>genus</hi> or ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall may act, as it may be ſaid to have members which are the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170879:21"/>
inſtruments of actions; but as himſelf confeſſeth, that though the members be in the <hi>genus,</hi> or comprehended under the <hi>genus,</hi> yet they reſpect it not as a <hi>genus,</hi> but as an integrall, ſo I ſay the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations are the operations of ſuch an integral of ſuch a kind, and not of the <hi>genus</hi> as a general. The generall <hi>in abſtracto</hi> work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not any <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (except notionall) but the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegralls work them.</p>
            <p>And whereas I proved in my eight argument. <hi>vind.</hi> 86. <hi>l.</hi> 8. that the whole Church is one integrall, by the ſeverall appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions given to it in Scripture, as Body, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Kingdom, tabernacle, houſe, building, temple, army, ſheep-fold, wheat-field, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline margQuotes">"M. <hi>Stone p.</hi> 33. ſaith, that theſe and ſuch appellations are indeed firſtly and properly appellations of an <hi>integrum,</hi> having analogy to <hi>totum integrale:</hi> but <hi>ſaith he</hi> this <hi>totum integrale</hi> is <hi>ſpecies ſpecialiſſima,</hi> or every individuall Church being <hi>ſpecies ſpecialiſſima,</hi> is alſo an <hi>integrum,</hi> and containeth members, and the <hi>genus</hi> comprehending all his <hi>ſpecies</hi> under him, it compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth the individuals with all their members under it, or within it ſelf. Hence thoſe appellations which are given to an individual Church are given to the Church in general, &amp;c. If a Church be a body, then this or that individual is a body, and all the members of it are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one and the ſame body, of one and the ſame Corporation.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, that then it wil follow that the whole Church is firſtly and properly an integral, of or under ſuch a kinde, <hi>viz.</hi> Society, or polity, becauſe thoſe appellations are firſtly and properly meant of that, and of particular Congregations but at ſecond hand.</p>
            <p>For firſt men are drawn into that, and into Congregations as a ſecondary and accidental thing, containing but parcels of the members of that great ſociety, or polity. It is clear that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is not meant in Scripture of a particular Congregation, but of the whole Church conſiſting of Jews and Gentiles entred into the Kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>We finde not a particular Congregation called the body of Chriſt, for then Chriſt ſhould have innumerable bodies, who hath but one, in the ſame kind, and that fitly join'd together and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170879:22"/>
compacted by that which every joint ſupplyeth, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.16. which M. <hi>Hooker,</hi> as I ſaid before, calls the external political Kingdom of Chriſt. Neither are particular Congregations called the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of Chriſt, for then he ſhould have many Kingdoms, in the ſame reſpect, whereas the Church militant is but one, conſiſting of many members. And Chriſt tells us the wheat-field is the world, and not particular Congregations. If a King hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Kingdoms, Cities, or Armies, though he ſpeaks of things that concern them all, and all alike, he doth not ſay my Kingdom, City, Army, but Kingdoms, Cities, Armies. If a man hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fields, houſes, floors, netts, loavs, and ſpeak of that which concerneth them all, de doth not ſay my field, houſe, floor, nett, loaf, but in the plural number, as of many: ſo would Chriſt have done if he had ſpoken or meant it primarily and intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally of many Churches or Congregations, but he bindes them up in the ſingular number, becauſe he meant but an Integral by all thoſe tearms, and the particular Congregations are but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells thereof; And differ no more, then when a cart-load of wheat is put into diverſe ſacks, whereof every one contains ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parcels of the load, becauſe it could not conveniently be all put into one, which though ſevered is accounted as, and ſold for one load of wheat, and when it is ſhot out makes but one heap. Or as a great common field divided by ſeveral meers or baulks, or a great meadow into ſeveral acres by dools, or marks, and ſo one man cutts and tends one acre, and another another, but theſe hinder not the integrality of the whole, much leſs do they make the whole meadow the <hi>genus,</hi> and the parts of it the <hi>ſpecies:</hi> ſo neither do the accidental and ſecondary differences between particular Congregations hinder the integrality of the whole Church, much leſſe make that the <hi>genus,</hi> and them the <hi>ſpecies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ninth Argument I brought to prove the whole Church an Integral, was from the ſeverall words which the Scripture uſeth to expreſſe the union of the members of the whole Church together, as <hi>added, builded together, fitly framed together, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted, all the body by joints and bands knit together,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>vind. p.</hi> 87. <hi>l.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>To this Argument M. <hi>Stone, p.</hi> 36. giveth the ſame anſwer, that he did to the former Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170879:22"/>But it is clear that the phraſes are meant of the whole Church primarily and immediately, and not of particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>This adding, joining, jointing, and building of the converted ones is firſt to the Kingdom, Body, and Houſe of Chriſt, and there is no other eſſential form added to them beſide Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by being ſevered out <hi>partiatim,</hi> by parcells into ſeveral Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations; that is a moſt accidental thing to them as Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, brought in by convenience, and neceſſity. Particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations; are but as ſeveral ridges in a wheat-field, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not the integrality of the whole field at all. As the dwelling of ſeveral men in ſeveral Towns in a Kingdom or Common-wealth, which Towns contain only ſome parcells of the ſubjects of that Kingdom or Common-wealth hinders not the integrali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the whole, though they be under particular officers for civil affairs: no more do the deiſtinction of viſible Chriſtians, into ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Congregations under ſeveral particular officers for Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall affairs, hinder the integrality of the whole Church. Firſt, men are ſubjects or deniſons of the Nation or Kingdom, and then have liberty according to their conveniences to live in what petty ſociety they pleaſe. So, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Though a man ſhould have ſeveral houſes in never ſo many Counties or Towns, and at ſomtime or other reſort to them all, and dwell for a time in them, yet this varies not his memberſhip of the Kingdom or Common-wealth, being meerly accidental to that relation. So, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denyed but that the ſeveral Congregations are integrals in reference to their own members, and ſo is any village in reference to the inhabitants, but in reference to the whole Church or Kingdom of Chriſt they are members, as the villages are of a Kingdom, or Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>How many bodies politick, and ſocieties in a Nation are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the greater body politick and ſociety of that Nation? ſo many leſs bodies Eccleſiaſtical make up the greater body Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical in a Nation; For it was foretold <hi>that the Kingdoms of this world ſhould become the Kingdoms of our Lord and of his Chriſt, Revel.</hi> 11.15. The Eccleſiaſtical polities in converted Kingdoms, are ſaid to be commenſurable to the civil. And by the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170879:23"/>
all the Chriſtians in all territories on earth make up the whole Church or whole viſible Kingdom of Chriſt in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world, becauſe it contains all the members thereof, who are Chriſt's ſubjects.</p>
            <p>And whereas M. <hi>Stone</hi> ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 37. that Baptiſm is a priviledg of a political member, as Circumciſion was a priviledg of the members of the Jewiſh Church, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. Thoſe <hi>Act.</hi> 2. were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Church, and then baptized.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not ſaid, they that were admitted into the Church were baptized, but they that gladly received his Word were baptized, <hi>verſe</hi> 14. ſo that Baptiſme admitted them into their firſt relation, and that was into the viſible Church.</p>
            <p>Neither can it be abſolutely ſaid that Circumciſion was a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of the Jewiſh Church, for the ſecond perſon, <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> that was circumciſed was not of it, nor any of the other Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Abraham,</hi> by <hi>Keturah,</hi> nor <hi>Eſau,</hi> and yet were circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed. Can wee thinke that <hi>Job</hi> and his friends ſo eminent for piety, and who ſacrificed to the true God with acceptance were uncircumciſed?</p>
            <p>And were all thoſe nations among whom they were chief men, if not rulers, which were of <hi>Abrahams</hi> poſterity by <hi>Ketu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah,</hi> and of <hi>Eſau's</hi> ſtock, heathens, uncircumciſed? The very name of <hi>Elihu</hi> ſheweth the contrary, which ſignifieth my God is <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah.</hi> So that it is more then probable that there were religious perſons and Countries after <hi>Abrahams</hi> time, beſide the Jews, if not before them, as M. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath well obſerved in his treatiſe upon Infants Baptiſm, and theſe no doubdt were circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed.</p>
            <p>It's true Religion did not very long continue among them, as among the Jews, but God would not have caſt off them, if they had not forſaken him.</p>
            <p>I grant that the ſeal of admiſſion is to be given to none but ſuch as are in covenant with God. But what covenant? The generall divine covenant, or the particular humane covenant? Surely into the generall covenant with God. The many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands bapttzed by <hi>John,</hi> and Chriſts diſciples, and the three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in <hi>Acts</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were indeed in covenant with the national Church
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170879:23"/>
of the Jews before baptiſm, becauſe the Church was then Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, but by this new ſigns they were admitted into the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Church by a new and Catholick ſeal, to which their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtanding gave them no right. And though as M. <hi>Stone,</hi> ſaith Obſignation with the initial ſeal of Baptiſm implyeth confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and admiſſion into the Church, yet it implyeth not confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration with this, or that, or any particular Church, or admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into it. Though <hi>Saul</hi> was baptized by <hi>Ananias</hi> at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> yet was it not as confederate either with the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> or <hi>Damaſcus</hi> whereof he had been a bitter perſecutor, but as a Convert to Jeſus Chriſt,</p>
            <p>And though haply <hi>Cornelius Acts</hi> 10. might be confederate with the Jewiſh Church, being a Proſelite, yet we know of no ſuch confederation of his kinſmen and near friends mentioned <hi>verſ.</hi> 24, who were Gentiles, and yet were all baptized. Neither do I think there was any implicite covenant to bind the Jewiſh Church together, or the Proſelites to the Jewiſh Church, beſides the divine general covenant with God, and yet for ought I know it had been as requiſite for the members of every Synagogue as for particular Congregations now, ſeeing they were lyable to cenſures there.</p>
            <p>With what particular Church were the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> confederate <hi>Act.</hi> 8.12? who were a little before bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Simons</hi> ſorceries, yet upon <hi>Philips</hi> preaching unto them, and their converſion unto Chriſt, they were baptized both men and women; the witch, and the bewitched.</p>
            <p>Surely <hi>Samaria</hi> was not confederate with <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they did not love one another ſo well: neither was there any inſtituted Church (as the new phraſe is) as yet in <hi>Samaria:</hi> neither was it a Congregationall Church, but the whole City with one accord: neither were there any particular officers ſet over them then, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could they enter into a particular Church covenant, as it is called, untill they were baptized, the generall covenant muſt precede the particular, and therefore were in no capacity to chooſe any officers over them, and yet they were baptized, and therefore baptiſm is no priviledge of a particular politicall Church-member, but of the general. And with what Church was the <hi>Jaylour</hi> as <hi>Philippi</hi> and his rude family in covenant? <hi>Act.</hi> 16.33.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170879:24"/>
who was a ruffianly heathen. Yet being converted at midnight, was baptized the ſame hour of the night, without asking leave of the Church there, if there were any.</p>
            <p>And for this particular covenant, though M. <hi>Stone</hi> ſaith <hi>p.</hi> 37. that it is a covenant not only between man &amp; man, but alſo between God &amp; man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But <hi>quojure?</hi> where is the inſtitution of it, or any hint of it in Scripture? It may be a promiſe before God, but not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God &amp; them; but between the people among themſelvs, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the people &amp; their Miniſter. The firſt and general covenant is between God and man, and is of divine inſtitution, but the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and particular is but humane and prudentiall, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot divolve any ſuch priviledg upon people unleſs the Lord had inſtituted it to that end. The univerſal Church is the whole politicall viſible kingdom of Chriſt on earth, and the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible beleevers are the matter thereof, and theſe believers are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, or, at leaſt, initiated into it by Chriſts officers, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of particular officers, but as Chriſts Miniſters and Ambaſſadours, <hi>to whom is committed the word of reconciliation;</hi> and are bound by their generall covenant to believe what God hath revealed, and obey what God hath commanded. As a Deniſon of <hi>England</hi> is bound to obey the Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> by being a ſubject thereof, and then theſe ſubjects are placed in ſeveral towns under particular civill officers, but no particular covenant is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of them to make them ſeverall villages, which for ought I know is as requiſite as a particular Church covenant. And thoſe towns conſiſt of Engliſh ſubjects, but they are not bound to the laws, becauſe members of thoſe towns, but becauſe ſubjects to the ſoveraign power of the whole nation. So Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are bound to perform obedience to Chriſt in all their rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and places, as ſubjects to Chriſt, and not by a particular covenant, except Chriſt had inſtituted any ſuch, as between man and wife, and there they are bound by both.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Stone</hi> bringeth two Aenigmaticall places to prove this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to be between God and man. <hi>Zech.</hi> 11.7.10.14 Of beauty &amp; bands. And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.5. <hi>As a bride-groom rejoyceth over his bride, ſo ſhall thy God rejoice over thee: and as a young man marrieth a virgin, ſo ſhall thy ſons marry thee.</hi> But I can find no evidence or hint in either of theſe places for a Congregationall Covenant. No nor
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170879:24"/>
in all the inſtances that are uſually given, <hi>viz,</hi> Gods Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> but we know that was the generall covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and man, and not Congregationall. And the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants made in the days of <hi>Aſa, Jehoſhaphat, Hezekiah, Joſiah; Nehemiah,</hi> are nothing to the purpoſe, for they were not Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall, but renewalls of their National Covenant with God, and they were the Church of God before they renewed this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and not conſtituted by the renewall of it.</p>
            <p>Neither doth <hi>Act.</hi> 9.26. which is alledged ſome, prove it. It is ſaid indeed that <hi>when Saul was come to Jeruſalem, he aſſayed to joyn himſelf to the diſciples, but they were all afraid of him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved not that he was a diſciple.</hi> But this joyning him to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, was to have comunion and ſociety with them, and not to be a particular Church member there. It is not ſaid he aſſayed to join himſelf to the Church, as a member, but to the diſciples, much leſſe is any particular covenant mentioned there.</p>
            <p>But as if one that was known to be an Apparitour, or Purſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, or Perſecutour in the Biſhops days ſhould aſſay to join him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with private Chriſtians in converſe, or ſome private meeting, they would be afraid of him; ſo was that caſe. But before that journey to <hi>Jeruſalem, ver.</hi> 15. it was ſhewed them, and by Chriſt to <hi>Ananias</hi> that he was a choſen veſſel to bear Chriſt's name be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Gentiles and Kings, as well as the children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And therefore might not join with the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as an officer or private member. Neither is it mentioned to which of the Congregations in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> he aſſayed to join him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, whereof no doubt there were great ſtore, ſeeing they had not great publick houſes to meet in, but private houſes onely, but it was to the Diſciples or Chriſtians there.</p>
            <p>Others bring a proof for this way from <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42.16. <hi>I will bring the blinde by a way that they knew not, I will lead them in paths that they have not known: I will make darkneſs light before them, and crooked things ſtraight.</hi> But this will not prove it, but may as well ſerve for any way that men can fancy. They may as well prove themſelves blind by this text, as prove a Congregational Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant from thence.</p>
            <p>Others argue that Church-relation is not a natural relation but a voluntary, and therefore muſt be by a Covenant or mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al agreement.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170879:25"/>A man ſay they will be my brother or kinſman whether I wil or no, becauſe it is a natural relation, but it is not ſo in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, ſo a man being born within the Church will be a Church-member by federal holineſs, and ſo a brother in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſenſe whether I will or no, being in the general Covenant. O! but ſay they, how can a woman become my wife, or a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come my ſervant, but by a voluntary Covenant? <hi>Anſ.</hi> no more can a man or woman of age be a Chriſtian, or member of the whole Church, but by being in Covenant with Chriſt the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and Lord of his Church, but what is this to a Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Covenant between member and member? Do ſervants when they enter into a family, or ſouldiers into a band or troop, make one covenant with the maſter or captain, and another with their fellow-ſervants, and fellow-ſouldiers? If haply they ſhould covenant together to be faithful in their places, and helpful one to another, and this ſhould tend to the great advantage of the maſter, or captain, and benefit of each other, yet this is not that which makes them that maſters ſervants, or that captains ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but the covenant with the maſter, or captain. Neither doth any maſter or captain require any ſuch ſecondary covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his ſervants or ſouldiers, and yet it is a voluntary relation, they enter into, but it is voluntary in reſpect of the maſter and ſervant, the captain and ſouldier, not in regard of the fellow-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and fellow-ſouldiers, that falls in neceſſarily.</p>
            <p>O! but it is voluntary what particular members I will join withall in a particular Congregation, I may chooſe of what par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſociety I will be a member.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> ſo I may chooſe in what Town in a Kingdom I will dwel, but I muſt take the inhabitants thereof to be my fellow-neighbours neceſſarily.</p>
            <p>So all the Churches of Chriſt ever took the Chriſtians cohabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with them within the civil bounds, to be their fellow-members of thoſe Churches.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> conſiſted of the Chriſtians inhabiting in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſo it may be ſaid of <hi>Corinth, Epheſus, Philippi,</hi> &amp;c. they did not pick and chooſe ſome out of one vicinity ſome out of another. If any were heretical or ſcandalous they had cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures to remove or amend them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170879:25"/>Now our civil bounds for Towns and Vicinities have been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſet for civil tranſactions, and cannot be by particular men altered, but by authority, and if all the inhabitants with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thoſe limits be in the viſible covenant with Chriſt and under his ſeal, and have publick houſes or Churches, as they are ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, but tropically called for publick worſhip, and a mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance appointed out of the revenues of thoſe Towns to maintain a Miniſter over them, and have a Miniſter of their own ſet over them, to whom, and his predeceſſors the Chriſtians of that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct have from generation to generation ſubmitted in the Lord, and enjoyed Gods Ordinances from them, I cannot ſee how without breach of order, and removing the ancient land-marks, and introducing confuſion, any particular member either of that Town or Church can of their own heads alter this, and pick Church-members whom they liſt, and where they liſt, and bring them into a particular Covenant to make a new particular Church, under colour to make a pure Church.</p>
            <p>I believe all the Church-members in <hi>Jeruſalem, Corinth, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippi,</hi> &amp;c. were not really godly, but many only externally, and many very looſe, and guilty of foul faults, 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 11. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5 <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18, 19. <hi>Jude</hi> 12.13, 16.</p>
            <p>Yet they did not leave them out, and inſtitute new Churches of choice members, but ſought to reclaim them. I ſcarce think all the members of the Churches in <hi>New-England</hi> are really god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or ſo judged of their Paſtors or fellow-members, and yet they do not pick the good from among the reſt, &amp; make new Churches of them, but keep the particular Churches ſtill anſwerable to the civil bounds. It is a bad way of cure to cut off the ſound mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers from the diſeaſed, and unite them together in a new body.</p>
            <p>It's true the civil bounds are heterogeneal to the Church, but ſo they were in <hi>Jeruſalem, Corinth, Epheſus,</hi> &amp;c. and yet they bounded them then, and denominated them, and ſo they do ſtill in <hi>New-England;</hi> and ſo the ſeveral ſhowres are to the ſeverall Seas, yet they bound and denominate them alſo. Indeed if Towns and Churches were to be conſtituted, they might have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bounds and quantities allowed them, and ſo might the Towns in <hi>New-England</hi> have, for there is no precept left in the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170879:26"/>
word to limit either of them, but the Churches would be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in thoſe towns: this is not to meaſure Churches by the acre, as ſome fooliſhly object. But we have both precept, exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and neceſſity requiring that the Churches ſhould be in a vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and not ſcattered abroad, ſo as the cannot conveniently meet together publickly on the Lords day, or watch over one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            <p>Yea, ſay ſome, if Churches were rightly conſtituted at firſt, we ought not to ſeparate from them, or gather Churches out of Churches, but ours were not ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> There are three things that I hear objected againſt our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Churches: Firſt, that it was not voluntary, but forced by authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> The members were not forced from heatheniſme to chriſtianity, but they became chriſtians many generations ago voluntarily, for ought I know: and for reforming of them, their predeceſſours, or ſucceſſours, either from Popery, which was a ſpirituall leproſy over-ſpreading the Church, or any other ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and reforming of them by authority and compulſion, I think it is no more then the Magiſtrate might, yea ought to do, and the godly Kings and Rulers in the Old Teſtament did, and were commended and bleſt for doing. Indeed a man cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly compell a woman to be his wife againſt her will; nor a man compell another to be his ſervant, or apprentice, but if they have once bound themſelvs by marriage, promiſe, or indenture, they may compel them to hold ſo, and to obey and reform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs. So is the caſe between Chriſt and his viſible Church.</p>
            <p>Secondly it is objected that we are not fit matter for a Church, and therefore not fit to be made Churches, or to be joined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> was there not as unfit matter in the Jewiſh Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſts coming, and yet the Church for the eſſence of it was the ſame then and now? yea was there not as unfit matter in the Churches in the Apoſtles time at <hi>Corinth</hi> and <hi>Phillippi</hi> &amp;c? ſee the texts before named, and tell me if we have worſe matter then there was, and yet what the Goſpell there ſaith, it ſaith to them that are under the Goſpell. Give an inſtance of any man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that ever profeſſed beleef in, and ſubjection to Chriſt in all
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170879:26"/>
the New Teſtament that ever was denyed admiſſion into the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, or that was caſt out meerly for want of the power of godlineſs. The Apoſtles inſtructed, informed, reproved, and ſought to amend them, and if they were hereticall, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious and obſtinate, excommunicated them; and that we allow and could heartily wiſh were ſtill done, and hope may in due time.</p>
            <p>Doth a ſhepherd turn the diſeaſed ſheep out of his flock quite, and feed only the ſound ones? no, he is to <hi>ſtrengthen the diſeaſed, and heal the ſick, and bind up the broken, and bring again that which was driven away, and ſeek up that which is loſt, Ezek.</hi> 34.4. Indeed it is requiſite he ſhould ſeparate the ſcabbed and diſeaſed from the reſt for a time, leſt they infect the reſt, and then having cured them to put them together into the ſame fold. Miniſters are ſent to <hi>the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael,</hi> as Chriſt commandeth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.6. and not to feed the ſound ones only that went not aſtray: and what manner of people Chriſt meant by thoſe loſt ſheep, I need not tell you, ſuch I believe as many in our age would have paſſed by, as the Prieſt and Levite did the wounded man in the parable, or counted goats rather then ſheep.</p>
            <p>Yea but the members of the Churches in the New Teſtament that grew ſo corrupt, did not appear ſo at their admiſſion into the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We know they were new Converts to the faith of Chriſt, and immediately admitted by baptiſm, even by thouſands of a day, and that when they were men grown, without any ſtrict enquiry of the truth of grace in them, and without any waiting for experience of their godly converſation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philip</hi> baptized <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer after his profeſſion of his belief in Chriſt, who yet was in the gall of bitterneſs and bond of iniquity, and of all men one would have thought he ſhould have been well tryed firſt, but was not.</p>
            <p>And the Apoſtle ſaith of ſome members in the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> that they had not the knowledg of God, he ſpake it to their ſhame. Surely if they had had it at their firſt admiſſion into Church, they would not have loſt it afterward, under the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of their teachers. Indeed they might corrupt in manners, or in judgment, but not loſe their knowledg, and grow ſotts.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170879:27"/>But there is a great deal of difference between a Church at the firſt conſtitution of it, when poſſibly they may pick choice mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, as they did at firſt in <hi>N. E.</hi> when they went over thither, men converted by the Miniſtry in Old England before they went thither; and a ſucceſſive Church in after ages, which conſiſt of a new generation, and ſeed of the former, <hi>aetas parentum pejor avis, tulit nos nequiores, mox daturos progeniem vitioſiorem.</hi> The Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſucceeding the Apoſtles age were not ſo pure as in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times, and yet then they were bad enough: and I fear the ſucceeding Churches in <hi>N. E.</hi> will not prove altogether ſo pure and eminent for ſincerity of grace and holy converſation as their firſt were; and yet our brethren do not hold that corrupt mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in ſuch a ſucceſſive Church doth unchurch them; and alas that is our condition in this nation, the Lord in mercy reform and amend us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly it is objected againſt us, that we are not rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, becauſe we want an explicite Congregational covenant, and ſo the true form.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Thus you ſee I am inforced to return to ſpeak of the Covenant again.</p>
            <p>But I anſwer, that all our Brethren for the Congregationall way do not unchurch us for want of that; and I think I may clear our Brethren in <hi>N. E.</hi> from that aſperſion: and ſome of our Brethren at home who have lately written, require but a mutuall agreement for joint worſhip of God, and I am ſure that may be found in our Congregations, and both have been, and might be more, but for theſe new ſcruples put into their minds.</p>
            <p>For my part I am not againſt an explicite Covenant in our Congregations, but wiſh they were as willing to it, as they are in many places willing to come to an agreement with their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters for their tithes, if they can get advantage thereby, as moſt what they do abundantly. For by ſuch a covenant, I conceive they ſhould be more bound to their Miniſters, as well as their Miniſters to them, and it might haply be a means to cauſe them to ſubmit the better to our inſtructions, reproofs, admonitions, inſpection and diſcipline; but I dare not ſtamp <hi>jus divinum</hi> upon it, neither do I find any hint of it in Scripture or primitive times, and therefore cannot believe there was any: but that they ſtood
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170879:27"/>
bound by their general Covenant to ſubmit to the Miniſters that were ſet over them in the Lord, in their ſeveral places. Neither dare I think it is that which gives people right to Gods Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor that it can divolve ſuch a priviledge upon the members that enter into it, to inveſt them with the power of the keys, to admit members, make officers, to inveſt and diveſt them, and have all Church power radically in themſelvs.</p>
            <p>I know M. <hi>Stone</hi> doth not make it the form of a particular Congregation, but the <hi>Cement</hi> rather; but truly as it is uſed or abuſed rather, by many about us, I fear it wil prove but untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered morter. For firſt people are ſo eager of it, that ſome people will join with Antipaedobaptiſts, Millenaries, and fift monarchy-men, or any ſect ſo they may but be in a covenant. Secondly, it is raiſed up as a partition wall between them and all the reſt of the Churches of Chriſt (though they be in implicite covenant, and agreement together, and with their Paſtors) ſo that they will not communicate with them, though never ſo religious, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and eminent Congregations, nor ſuffer any of them, though never ſo godly and ſo acknowledged by them to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with themſelves. They will not baptize any of our children, nor ſuffer us to baptize any of theirs: nay they will not ſo much as ſtay to ſee any of our children baptized, if they be occaſionally at a Lecture where any ſuch child is to be baptized, though they know the parents be very godly, and the Miniſter bee godly that is to baptize them, and though there bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing offenſive in the manner of adminiſtration of Baptiſm, but run out, as if the Church were on fire over their heads. Thirdly, as it occaſioneth the breach of many marriages that elſe would be ſuitable, ſo it many times cauſeth great breaches after marriages between man and wife, even to the antichriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, or at leaſt to the unchurching one of another, and cauſeth jarrs and alienation of affections, and vain janglings and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes, and unchriſtian heats and animoſities inſtead of ſweet Chriſtian love, unity, and communion, and mutual edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Fourthly, it exceedingly hinders family-duties, that they can neither join ſo cordially together in praier, having ſuch ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter thoughts one of another, nor yet in Catechizing of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies; nor calling over the Word publickly taught, or calling
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170879:28"/>
children and ſervants to an account for what they have heard publickly, becauſe one runs to one Town to the publick Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and another to another, and one draws ſome of the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one way, and the other another. Fiftly it is uſed as a means to enthral the members that are entred into it, ſo that though they marry out of that Town, or remove their dwellings out by neceſſity or for convenience, and dwell never ſo far diſtant from them, yet muſt they remain members of that Congregation, and may not join with any other Church, without their leave and diſmiſſion, which they will not give, except that Church with which they would join be conſtituted, or inſtituted, as the new phraſe is, by an explicite Covenant, as ſad experience hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: nay, are not permitted to join with a Congregation, though never ſo eminent for godlineſs and reformation; no, not though the perſon acknowledgeth, not only the Miniſter to be godly and eminent, but alſo the inſtrument under God of the work of grace in him formerly.</p>
            <p>Yea it is accounted no leſs then ſpiritual adultery to depart from them after they are thus joined, without their diſmiſſion, which they will not give, except to a new inſtituted Church of the ſame kind.</p>
            <p>If it be ſuch a ſnare, it is good for ſingle perſons to keep out of that bond untill they ſee how and where God will diſpoſe of them by marriage: and for married perſons to get as long leaſes of their farmes as they can, and keep their yoke-fellows as long as they can, for if they dye, they lay a great bar in their own way againſt a ſecond marriage, except to one of their own Church, or one of like conſtitution. I do not conceive that God ever bound any man or woman to ſuch inconveniences, onely they muſt not marry, but in the Lord, ſaith the Apoſtle; nor yet do our brethren in <hi>New-England</hi> put any ſuch yoke upon the Diſciples necks, as far as I underſtand; neither do I think a brother or ſiſter is in bondage in ſuch a caſe, but this uſe or rather abuſe is made of this Covenant by ſome in our Country.</p>
            <p>It is a harſh cenſure which M. <hi>Sam. Mather,</hi> a young man as I hear, hath given againſt ſuch as are not of his judgement in this point, in his preface before M. <hi>Stones</hi> Book, <q rend="inline margQuotes">"As if the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170879:28"/>
dreadful revenges of God, either for perſonal pollutions, or for ſinfull complyance with former devices, or wayes of men in the things of his houſe, or for ſecret contempt of the ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and power of the Goſpel, are gone forth in penal blindneſs, and other blaſting ſtrokes, upon the ſouls of ſome in theſe times.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As if this were the very pattern ſhewed in the Mount, and the very faſhion and form of the houſe ſhewed to the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel, Ezek.</hi> 43.10.11. as is there intimated. But we pray you is it a pattern revealed in the Word of God, or by inſpiration onely? If it be ſet down in the Word of God, we beſeech you be pleaſed to ſhew it unto us, and point us to the texts of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture that hold it forth: we hope ſome of us deſire to fear and ſerve God in truth, as well as among you. How many worthy Martyrs, Miniſters, and eminent Chriſtians have dyed for the faith, and in the faith, and gone to heaven, before either M. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> or this Covenant were born; were they all ſtrucken with the dreadfull revenges of God in penal blindneſs and blaſting ſtrokes? I believe our brethren will not ſay ſo.</p>
            <p>And if this Church-Covenant hath no better effects elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, then it hath in theſe parts, as I ſhewed before, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it were better it never had been deviſed, or were made <hi>Nehuſhtan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>Stone</hi> calls the Univerſal Church, <hi>Totum genericum exiſtens,</hi> as M. <hi>Hooker</hi> did alſo in his book; of which I ſaid <hi>vind.</hi> 40 that it is nothing elſe but <hi>integrum ſimilare.</hi> But I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg that though <hi>totum genericum exiſtens</hi> may be <hi>integrum ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare,</hi> yet is not always ſo. It is ſo when all of that kind that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſteth is bound together in one <hi>copula</hi> or bond.</p>
            <p>As if all the Sand in the world were on one heap, or all the Gold in the world were of one lump, they were integralls.</p>
            <p>Or if there be ſuch a bird as the Phoenix, it is <hi>totum genericum exiſtens,</hi> and yet it is an integrall. But if there be no ſuch bond, then it is not an integral<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet they are not that thing <hi>in genere,</hi> nor the genus of all that kind. But the univerſall viſible Church, though it be <hi>totum genericum exiſtens,</hi> i. e. all of that kind of ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety or body that exiſteth, yet it is an integral, becauſe it is bound together by an externall viſible bond, yea bonds, as hath been
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170879:29"/>
ſhewed before; &amp; that Covenant with God in Chriſt, &amp; the ſeal of Baptiſme, which makes them of that kind compleatly, makes them alſo of that integral, <hi>eâ formali ratione,</hi> and they cannot be of that kind, except they enter in as members of that integrall.</p>
            <p>I acknowledg alſo that the inſtance of the nature of a flock not reſerved in one ſheep, or of a Corporation reſerved in one man, mentioned <hi>vind p.</hi> 79, which M. <hi>Stone</hi> puts me twice in mind of, was miſplaced and miſapplied there; for the flock is not the <hi>genus</hi> of ſheep, nor the Corporation of the men in it; but both flock and Corporation are each of them integrals, and ſo is the whole Church.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Stone</hi> alſo findes fault that I ſaid <hi>vind. p.</hi> 78, that that which exiſteth in the individuall is <hi>ipſa cauſa materialis individui.</hi> If he like not that expreſſion, let him take the former mentioned but three lines before it, it is <hi>pars eſſentialis individui,</hi> for it goeth to the conſtitution of the eſſence of it, but it is not the <hi>genus</hi> of the integral, or that thing <hi>in genere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas I ſaid <hi>vind. p.</hi> 216. that I do not mean that the univerſall Church is firſt in regard of conſtitution of the whole politicall Kingdome of Chriſt by aggregation and combinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe the particular Congregations muſt exiſt before they can be combined and aggregated. I now declare that the firſt matter of the univerſall Church are particular viſible bleleevers, that are drawn into the generall Covenant, and theſe are ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily combined into particular combinations, and ſo the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binations of Congregations in the univerſall Church is not the firſt combination, but a ſecondary, and in the diſtribution or <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalyſis</hi> of the Church-Catholick, they are accounted members of the diſtribution, but in the <hi>geneſis</hi> or conſtitution, the particular members are firſt conſtitutive.</p>
            <p>I ſhall alſo be willing that the eighth way whereby the whole Church may be accounted the prime Church, namely <hi>cognitione ſive noſcibilitate perfecta,</hi> mentioned <hi>vind.</hi> 218. 219. and 253 may be left out, becauſe it is more proper to a genericall nature then an integrall: and ſo may be ſaid of the Church as it is a kind of ſociety differing from others, rather then as it is an integral con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of members, for there the members are firſt conſidered.</p>
            <p>And to M. <hi>Stones</hi> objection againſt what I ſaid <hi>vin. p.</hi> 219 and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170879:29"/>
220, that the priority of the Church-Catholick in reſpect of the particular, is like the priority of a Kingdome to the parts of it, or of a Corporation to the parts of it, which ſaid I is not meant in a mathematicall or techtonicall conſideration.</p>
            <p>I anſwer once again, that the members of the univerſal Church which are the particular viſible believers, are, as it is an integral, in conſideration before the whole, becauſe the whole is made up of them, as a kingdom of all the members of the kingdom, and all the towns in it are made up of the members of the kingdom, and ſo are all particular Congregations of the members of the univerſal Church; and in the diſtribution of the whole into parts there the whole is conſidered firſt, and then is diſtributed not onely into particular members, but into combined members dwelling in ſeverall Countries, or leſs ſecondary combinations, and ſo even thoſe ſecondary combinations may be ſaid to make up that whole, for of ſuch parts as the whole is diſtributed into, of ſuch it is alſo conſtituted.</p>
            <p>But the particular Congregations are made up onely of ſuch as are members of the whole Church, and they are entred into that body, before they are conſidered as members of the petty ſeveral ſocieties.</p>
            <p>And for the unity and priority of the Catholick Church. M. <hi>Cotton</hi> upon <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.9 <hi>p.</hi> 191. hath this paſſage. <q rend="inline margQuotes">"The Church is one, <hi>i. e.</hi> at unity or brotherly love one with another, as one body, though ſcattered into many places, as <hi>England, Scotland Germany,</hi> &amp;c. in all Chriſtendom. Some Churches are more chaſt, mild, and unſpotted then others, even of the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet ſuch are but few, and though few, yet at entire u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity as one body. <hi>The onely one of her mother, the choiceſt one of her that bare her.</hi> In the Hebrew phraſe, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> the whole is the mother, the parts are the members. The true Catholick Church of Chriſt is the mother of all the reformed daughters, and theſe daughter-Churches that are moſt chaſt, and mild, and undefiled they are beſt eſteemed, and beſt beloved of the mother Catholick Church.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Whence we note, that there is a Church-Catholick, and that particular Churches are the daughters of that Church, and theſe daughters are parts and members of that one body, and therefore
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170879:30"/>
not <hi>ſpecies,</hi> and this muſt conſiſt of the ſame nature that the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers do which conſtitute it, and ſo be viſible, elſe I know not what ſenſe to make of M. <hi>Cottons</hi> words.</p>
            <p>It ſeemeth very ſtrange to me that whereas the Scripture ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſo much of the Kingdom of Chriſt, the Kingdom of God, the Kingdom of his dear Son, and Chriſt's everlaſting Kingdom, and of the amplitude thereof from ſea to ſea, and from the flood to the worlds end, that all this ſhould be nothing elſe but a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <hi>in genere,</hi> or a general Kingdom in a Logical notion, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending none but a few particular Congregations, conſiſting of 7. 10. 20. 40. or 60. perſons therein, united in an explicite Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational Covenant, and no univerſal or large integral King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom whereof they are but members or parcels.</p>
            <p>As if a King ſhould be famous for a large and glorious King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and when all coms to all, it is nothing but a few little Iſlands that ſtand independent at a diſtance one from another, and have no other union together but that they are all ruled by the ſame King, and are as ſo many petty kingdoms under him, having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do one with another, but only to live in love and peace together. I conceive this is a very great eclipſing of the glory of Chriſt in his Kingly office and honour. I ſhould liſten after the interpretation that our brethren give of <hi>Act.</hi> 8.3. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.13. of <hi>Saul's</hi> perſecuting the Church; and <hi>Act.</hi> 2.47. of the adding of people to the Church; and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. of God's ſetting Officers in the Church to be meant <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, if the Scripture did not ſo abundantly ſpeak of the unity and amplitude of the Church, and bonds whereby all of that ſort are bound together in an Integral. But for my part I cannot ſee how it is poſſible for a man to enter compleatly into that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or kind, but he muſt withal enter into that Integral, and that this Integral muſt receive not only ſeveral Congregations, but even whole Chriſtian Nations, and even ſingle perſons converted, though they ſhould not bee joined in any particular Congregations. I ſhould have added many other things, but that I would not exceed the bounds of a Poſtſcript, and the Preſs ſtayeth for this. The Lord guide us into all truth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
